<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Daniel Sennertus his meditations setting forth a plain method of living holily and dying happily / written originally in Latin, and now translated into English.</title>
            <author>Sennert, Daniel, 1572-1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 222 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 99 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59194</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2536</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19038</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12561044</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12561044</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63173</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59194)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63173)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 703:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Daniel Sennertus his meditations setting forth a plain method of living holily and dying happily / written originally in Latin, and now translated into English.</title>
                  <author>Sennert, Daniel, 1572-1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 177, [1] p., 1 leaf of plates.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Sam. Keble ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: prelim. p. [16].</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>First edition.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Meditations.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:63173:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of reclining man meditating on death</figDesc>
                  <head>
                     <q>It is appointed for all men once to die</q>
                  </head>
                  <q>
                     <p>Are not my days few? Ceaſe then, and let me alone that I may take comfort a little: Before I go whence I shall not return, even to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land of darkneſs, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> shadow of death,</p>
                     <bibl>Job: 10: 20: 21. </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>For I know that thou wilt bring me to death. &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe appointed for all living,</p>
                     <bibl>Job: 30.23.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63173:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Daniel Sennertus</hi> HIS MEDITATIONS.</p>
            <p>Setting forth a plain Method OF LIVING HOLILY AND DYING HAPPILY.</p>
            <p>Written Originally in <hi>Latin,</hi> and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> qui ſe me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt inquilinos eſſe, &amp; in conducto habitare, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> je gerunt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s gravatim excunt: ita q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lligunt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>micilium c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>poris ad h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eve tempus à natura commadatum e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe, &amp; vivunt temper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aius, &amp; libentius moriuntur, </p>
               <bibl>Sen</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ala mors putanda non eſt quam bond vita praeceſſit, neque enim facit malam mortem niſi quod ſequitur ipſam mortem</p> 
               <bibl>St. <hi>Aug. de Civ. Dei.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Sam. Keble,</hi> at the <hi>Great Turks Head,</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> over againſt <hi>Fetter-Lane,</hi> MDCXCIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:63173:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63173:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>WHEN Death ſhall put a period to our Lives, we muſt appear before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt, and according as we have behav'd our ſelves here, we ſhall be conſigned to an Eternity either of Bliſs or Woe. Which <hi>four laſt things,</hi> being of ſuch vaſt concern and moment to us, have always been eſteemed moſt worthy of our ſerious thoughts and contemplations: for what is there that can more powerfully move a Man to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the ways of ſin, and walk in the paths of virtue, and conform himſelf to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Will, than a conſtant Meditation on theſe things? To what purpoſe ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:63173:3"/>any one endeavour to encreaſe his ſubſtance by fraud, injuſtice, and oppreſſion; or ſet his heart on Honours and Riches, ſtill coveting to <hi>add field to field,</hi> if he doth but think with himſelf, that when Death approaches he muſt leave all theſe worldly things behind him, and that for ought he knows even <hi>this Night, his Soul may be required of him, and then whoſe ſhall all theſe things be?</hi> Who is there that would not be afraid of commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſhameful and abominable crimes, even in ſecret, where no eye can ſee him? when he conſiders that in the laſt day of Judgment, the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be diſcloſed, and all his moſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate actions be laid open before Men and Angels? and that he muſt give a ſtrict account of all his thoughts, words, and deeds before the great <hi>Judge of all the Earth?</hi> Who would dare to drown himſelf in voluptuouſneſs and the ſinful luſts of the fleſh, if he did but remember, that for the enjoyment of ſuch vain and momentary pleaſures, he muſt endure the moſt exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite torments of Hell to all eternity? Who is there that would not chearfully walk in the narrow path that leadeth unto life, though he were ſure in the way to meet with <hi>tribulation, diſtreſs, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution,
<pb facs="tcp:63173:3"/>bonds and impriſonment, famin and nakedneſs, peril and Sword?</hi> if he did but lift up the eyes of his mind, and behold that <hi>exceeding and Eternal Weight of Glory which is laid up in Heaven,</hi> for thoſe that ſuffer for Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Since therefore the frequent conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe things hath ſo much force and efficacy to invite Men to vertue, and deter them from ſin; I was eaſily induced to tranſlate the following Meditatious into our Native Language, notwithſtanding the multitude of other books that have been written on the ſame Subject: for Men being generally ſo forgetful of their morta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, eſpecially in time of health and proſperity, there can never be too many admonitions given, to <hi>put them always in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of theſe things, although they know them already.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Book was firſt publiſh'd in Latin at <hi>Wittembergh</hi> in the year of our Lord <hi>1636.</hi> By that famous Phyſition <hi>Daniel Sennertus;</hi> a Man well known to the learned World, eſpecially to the Gentlemen of his own faculty, for his excellent works in that Art: but beſides what he ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly profeſs'd he was a ſpiritual Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian alſo, and took care to <hi>deliver ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:63173:4"/>wholſom Medicines that all the Diſeaſes of our Souls might be healed;</hi> and that both Soul and Body might live for ever; thereby imitating our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, who as <hi>he healed all manner of ſickneſs, and all manner of Diſeaſes amongſt the People,</hi> ſo he alſo <hi>called all ſinners to repentance,</hi> and exhorted them to enter into the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>It may not be amiſs here to add a ſhort account of this Book,
<note place="margin">M. Hen. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Memor. Medicorum. p. 105. Francof. 1676.</note> and its Author from one who hath given us ſome memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of his life, in an Oration ſpoken the year after his Deceaſe in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of <hi>Wittembergh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The innocency</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity of his Life, and that Humanity which he ſhew'd to all Men did great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advance his renown: ſuch was his love and care for Religion, that he ſuffer'd nothing to be prefer'd before it; He had perfectly digeſted in his mind the rules and precepts of it, which he as carefully endeavoured to manifeſt in his life, leaſt he ſhould appear to be in Word only and not in Deed, a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; the duty whereof he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded did not more conſiſt in the knowledge, than in the practice of
<pb facs="tcp:63173:4"/>Chriſtian virtues: wherein that he might be the better exerciſed, he had judiciouſly and accurately deſcribed THE NO-CHRISTIAN CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIAN: for he thought if vice were throughly known, the contrary virtue would thereby be repreſented more fair and ſtrong: As the People of</hi> Laced<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mon <hi>recommended ſobriety to their Children, by bidding them look on the filthineſs of Drunkards: On the ſame deſign there is now lately publiſh'd by himſelf, a moſt judicious Treatiſe of THE WAY TO LIVE HOLILY AND DY HAPPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY. For he cannot without great hazard dye well, who hath led an ill life, and ſcarcely can any one live as he ſhould, that is ignorant of the right method, or doth not diligently exerciſe himſelf in it: He dyed on the 21ſt. Day of</hi> July <hi>in the Year of our Lord 1637. When he had not yet been ill four Days.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some may perhaps object againſt the compoſure of this Book, that whereas the deſign of it is to prepare us to dye happily, ſo many Chapters ſhould be ſpent in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and more remote preparation for Death, whilſt we are in our health and vigour;
<pb facs="tcp:63173:5"/>and but one to be allotted for that more immediate and particular preparation which is to be performed when Death ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches.</p>
            <p>This may indeed ſeem a great obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Worldly Men, who ſcarcely ever think of dying, till they ſee they can live no longer: But the devout Chriſtian knows that a Death Bed is very unfit both for time and place for ſo great a work; that all his life is little enough to <hi>work out his own Salvation,</hi> and to prepare himſelf for an happy Eternity; and that if he demeans himſelf <hi>ſoberly, righteouſly, and godlily,</hi> whilſt he lives <hi>in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent World,</hi> he ſhall have the leſs to do when ever it ſhall pleaſe God to call him out of it.</p>
            <p>Let not any then deſpiſe theſe counſels and directions, as if they belonged only to ſick and Dying Men; but rather conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that if they daily exerciſe themſelves in the uſe and practiſe of them, whilſt they are in their health and strength, they will reap the greater benefit by them, when they come to die, and will depart this life with a comfortable aſſurance of God's favour; but it is to be feared that they will find themſelves very ill prepar'd for an happy departure hence at the time of
<pb facs="tcp:63173:5"/>their diſſolution, who when they were well, us'd all their endeavours to put the thoughts of death out of their minds.</p>
            <p>Be therefore intent and diligent in reading and meditating on Lectures of Mortality, and learn to die whilſt you live. Put on the perſon of a dying man, even now whilst the ſtrength of your mind and body remains perfect and entire in you: Do thoſe things now which you would deſire to do when you are a dying, and then when ever the tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> draws nigh, that you muſt die indeed, you will find all thoſe holy preparations with which you ſo frequently exerciſed your ſelf in your life time, will be wonderfully helpful and ſubſervient to you in that your laſt hour: All the Divine Comforts and Conſolations with which you entertain'd your ſelf during the <hi>days of your Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage</hi> here, will come afreſh into your mind, and you will have little more to do, than to rejoyce in the reflexions on a well ſpent life, and to <hi>commend your Soul into the Hands of God, as into the Hands of a faithful Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, and moſt Merciful Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when ever any ſickneſs ſeizeth on you, remember that it doth not come by chance, but by the hand of God,
<pb facs="tcp:63173:6"/>and thank him for his Fatherly Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction towards you: Commit your ſelf to his Divine Providence, and rely not too much on the Phyſitians help, which we find king <hi>Aſa</hi> reprov'd for in Holy Scripture: Yet according to the advice of the Son of <hi>Sirach, Honour the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian,</hi> and make uſe of ſuch means as God and Nature offer, but let your great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt care be, for the health of your Soul: For ſince a dreadful Eternity ſucceeds the ſhort moment of your life. What mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs would it be to employ all your Care and Diligence about this vain life, which paſſeth away like a ſhaddow, and to make no proviſion for your everlasting State in the other World, till you are brought to the very confines of it.</p>
            <p>But, O Chriſtian, if you are wiſe, be every day thinking, that you <hi>muſt ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put off this your Earthly Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, even as the Lord hath ſhewn you:</hi> And in any ſickneſs that befalls you, first reconcile your ſelf to God, and then you may be aſſured, that either he will make the means you uſe conducive to the health of your Body, or elſe will make your Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and even Death it ſelf healthful to your Soul.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table">
            <pb facs="tcp:63173:6"/>
            <head>A TABLE Of the Chapters in the enſuing Treatiſe, comprizing the Sum of Chriſtian Religion.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHAP. I. <hi>IT is appointed for all Men once to die.</hi> p. 1.</item>
               <item>Chap. II. <hi>And at death all things in the World are to be left behind.</hi> p. 4.</item>
               <item>Chap. III. <hi>But after death there remains another life, and death is the paſſage either to Eternal Happineſs or Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> p. 10</item>
               <item>Chap. IV. <hi>All Men after death must ſtand before the Judgment Seat of God.</hi> p. 16.</item>
               <item>Chap. V. <hi>And ſome ſhall be Tranſlated
<pb facs="tcp:63173:7"/>into Eternal life, abounding with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Felicities.</hi> p. 22.</item>
               <item>Chap. VI. <hi>Whilſt others ſhall be caſt headlong into the unſpeakable Torments of Hell.</hi> p. 27.</item>
               <item>Chap. VII. <hi>And ſince they only are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Bleſſed life who die well; it therefore concerns all Men to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful how they live, and to prepare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for a Bleſſed death, as a thing very difficult. Now this Preparation is either general, and to be exerciſed every day; or particular, to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed when death approaches.</hi> p. 36.</item>
               <item>Chap. VIII. <hi>Towards this general and daily Preparation it is requiſite for a Man, first to conſider the certainty of death, the ſhortneſs of life, and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the hour of death.</hi> p. 38.</item>
               <item>Chap. IX. Secondly, <hi>Not to fear Death.</hi> p. 52.</item>
               <item>Chap. X. Thirdly, <hi>That he perform the Duty of a Chriſtian.</hi> p. 61.</item>
               <item>Chap. II. <hi>Now the Duty of a Chriſtian conſiſts chiefly in true Repentance: And firſt in ſorrow for ſin.</hi> p. 68.</item>
               <item>Chap. XII. Secondly, <hi>In an Humble Reliance on the Mercies of God, and in Faith in Chriſt.</hi> p. 73.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:63173:7"/>
               <item>Chap. XIII. Thirdly, <hi>In an Holy life.</hi> p. 79.</item>
               <item>Chap. XIV. <hi>And he lives well, who loves God above all things.</hi> p. 85.</item>
               <item>Chap. XV. <hi>And his Neighbour as himſelf,</hi> p. 93.</item>
               <item>Chap. XVI. <hi>And to this end, he is to ſtrive againſt all Capital and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ormeus ſins, which are contrary to the love of God and his Neighbour.</hi> p. 97.</item>
               <item>Chap. XVII. <hi>And that the Christian may the better perſevere in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of Virtue and Repentante, it may be very uſeful for him to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Diary, or a daily Form of Devotion.</hi> p. 118</item>
               <item>Chap. XVIII. <hi>The particular prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for death conſiſts in two things; one whereof concerns the ſick Perſon, and the other his Neighbour: The firſt is, that the dying Man make his peace with God, and fortifie his mind againſt all thoſe Temptations which uſually inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate themſelves at this time: The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is, that he be in perfect Love and Charity with all Men, and rightly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of all his Worldly concerns.</hi> p. 140.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:63173:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:63173:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:63173:9"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Feb.</hi> 15. 1693/4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Guil. Lancaſter</hi> R P D, <hi>Henrico</hi> Epiſ. <hi>Lond</hi> à Sacris Domeſtic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 13 line 5. for <hi>Theogenis,</hi> read <hi>Theognis.</hi> p. 45. l. 2. f. <hi>neglact,</hi> r. <hi>neglect.</hi> p. 52. l. 15. f. <hi>the,</hi> r. <hi>a.</hi> p. 53. l. 28. f. <hi>World,</hi> r. <hi>World.</hi> p. 69. l. 19. f. <hi>Mirrior</hi> r. <hi>Mirroir.</hi> p. 81. l. 9. f. <hi>in,</hi> r. <hi>and.</hi> p. 103. l. 23. f. <hi>this,</hi> r. <hi>his.</hi> p. 108. l. 28. f. <hi>Languiſh,</hi> r. <hi>Anguiſh.</hi> p. 127. l. 11. f. <hi>putriſying,</hi> r. <hi>putrify.</hi> p. 172. l. 10. f. <hi>deſire.</hi> r. <hi>deſerve.</hi> p. 173. l. 8. f. <hi>make,</hi> r. <hi>maketh.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="meditations">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63173:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Daniel Sennertus</hi> HIS MEDITATIONS OF <hi>Living holily and dying happily.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>That all muſt die.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE are taught both by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and Heathen Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that we muſt all die; whilſt they often inculcate, that it is appointed unto men once to die;
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.27. Wiſd. 7.6. 1 Kings 2.2.</note> that all-Men have one entrance into Life, and the like going out; that Death is the way of all the Earth: Thus alſo <hi>Ovid</hi> ſpeaks,
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tendimus huc omnes, metam properamus ad unam:</l>
                        <l>Omnia-ſub leges mors vocat atra ſuas.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>We all paſs ſwiftly on to the ſame state.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And all are ſubject to the Laws of Fate.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:63173:10"/>
               <p>And <hi>Horace</hi> —
<note place="margin">Lib. 2. Od. 18.</note>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Omnes manet una nox, &amp; calcanda ſemel via lethi.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A long dark Night will all the World o're ſpread:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And all, the rugged paths of Death muſt tread.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q> But much more plainly doth daily experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and the Funerals we continually ſee go by our doors, admoniſh us of our mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.
<note place="margin">Sen. Ep. 100.</note> 
                  <hi>Omnis dies, omnis hora,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, every hour, ſhews us we are nothing, and by ſome freſh Arguments puts us in mind of the frailty of our Natures, which we too eaſily forget, and forceth us to look on death, whilst we are thinking of abiding here for ever.</hi> There is no man can promiſe himſelf an immunity from death, by any of thoſe things which are wont to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh Men from the reſt of Mankind. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Age nor Sex, no condition or ſtate of life, neither learning, nor honours, nor riches, nor beauty, nor pleaſure, can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend any one from death; Young and Old, Kings and Beggars, the Wiſe and the Ignorant, the Fair and the Deformed, muſt all die:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63173:10"/>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Pallida mors aequo pulſat pede pauperum ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernas,
<note place="margin">Hor lib. 1. Od 4.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Regumque turres. Neque ulla eſt aut magno aut parvo lethi fuga.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pale Death goes into all a like;
<note place="margin">Id. Sat. 6. lib. 2. Serm.</note> as well</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Towers of Princes, as the poorest Cell;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nor is there any one can flie from Death.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q> Thus as there is no difference obſervable in the birth of men, ſo neither is there in their death.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LOrd let me know my end, and the number of my dayes, that I may be certified how long I have to live: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thou haſt made my dayes as it were a ſpan long, and my age is even as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in reſpect of Thee: Verily every man living is altogether Vanity: We come up as a flower, and are cut down, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver continue in one ſtay: Lord ſo teach me to number my dayes, that I may apply my heart unto wiſdom: Grant that I may not be one moment forgetful of my mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality; and knowing that I muſt die, let me never think of ſetting up my reſt here.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:63173:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The Conſideration of thoſe things which happen at Death.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe devout Chriſtian ought not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be perpetually mindful of his own mortality, but alſo ſeriouſly to conſider what Death is, and what uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly befalls men, when they are dying, and when they are dead: Imagine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore before your eyes a man now on the Confines of Death, juſt ready to give up the Ghoſt fix this object in your mind, and every day revolve it in your thoughts: See how he lies dying, almoſt without breath: His Body loſes all its beauty and comelineſs, and begins to ſmell of the Earth from whence it was taken, and none of its members perform their fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: And yet this is that Body which not long ſince was ſo ſumptuouſly fed, ſo delicately cloath'd, and nurs'd up with ſo much care and coſt: Then a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to deſpiſe his Gold and Silver, his Jewels and Apparel, his Riotings and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63173:11"/>when he finds no aſſiſtance from them, either againſt his Sickneſs or his Death; he ſees all his worldly delights are vaniſhed away, and others ready to poſſeſs his Honours and Riches; and an afflicting thought it is to him to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that for the obtaining theſe very things, he hath undergone ſo much toil and labour, and hath committed ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſins. And hence will ariſe many conflicts of mind, many tormenting thoughts and unquiet hours: Sometimes the acuteneſs of his Diſeaſe afflicts him, ſometimes his Conſcience wounds him, and Satan ſets before his eyes the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his Sins, which now appear more vile and heinous than ever before he thought them to be. Sometimes he is diſtracted, when he remembers how much time he hath prodigally ſpent in vanity and folly, and that now he muſt give a ſtrict account of all his thoughts, words, and actions; ſometimes his Soul is grieved by the temptations of the Devil driving him to deſpair, and ſhewing him, the direful puniſhments of Hell-fire. Thus alſo when a man begins to think he can live no longer, he then conſiders he muſt leave his Wiſe and Children, his Kinsfolks and Friends, his Riches and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63173:12"/>and every thing that was dear to him here; and this leads him to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der further, that in a ſhort time his Soul muſt be ſeparated from his Body; and that he muſt paſs into another ſtate of Life: Then if a man hath not duly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared himſelf for Death, nor reconciled himſelf to God, with what anguiſh ſhall his Soul be tormented, when he can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect no help from any of thoſe things which he before ſo much accounted of: To live longer is not permitted him, and to die is intolerable: Then he calls to mind his former ſins which he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and ſees the time of his exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and of the divine vengeance is at hand: If he looks back upon his paſt life, all the dayes he has ſpent ſeems but a moment of time: If he looks for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward on that infinite ſpace of Eternity which is to come, he then grieves that he hath preferr'd ſuch vain delights, and of ſuch ſhort continuance, before an eternal weight of Glory and Happineſs: And theſe things do ſo diſquiet him, that no room is left for any comfortable thoughts; for Death now approaching, he will ſcarcely have either time or ſtrength to think on any thing for his good; to what purpoſe is it to give wholeſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63173:12"/>to adminiſter profitable Counſels to one, whoſe Senſes are impair'd by the violence of his Diſeaſe, and whoſe mind and underſtanding are weakned and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd by the Indiſpoſition of his Body: For whilſt he is conſidering that he is not prepar'd for Death as he ought, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracts himſelf with the thoughts of his ſad Condition, his Eyes begin to grow dim, and his Ears deaf, his Tongue fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and his Memory and Reaſon fail him.</p>
               <p>Do thoſe things therefore now whilſt thou art in Health, and God alloweth thee Time and Strength, which thou canſt not but think Reaſonable ſhould be done, at thy laſt Hour, arm thy ſelf betimes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all thoſe Evils and Temptations, which commonly befall Men at the time of Death; and ſeeing that neither Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, nor Honours, nor Pleaſures, nor Friends, can prolong our Lives for one hour, nor free us from thoſe Cares and Anxieties, which are wont to diſturb Men when they are dying, believe it, it is deſperate madneſs to undergo ſo much labour for the ſake of them; and contrariwiſe to neglect thoſe things which would help us toward the attainment of Everlaſting Happineſs.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:63173:13"/>
               <p>And now O Man, think what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of thee after death: As ſoon as thou art dead, every one, even thy neareſt and beſt Friends, thy Wife and Children, and Kinsfolk, will fly from thy Corps, and will not be able to endure the ſight of thee; before they were pleaſed with thy Embraces; but now thy very preſence is Ghaſtly and Terrible: Here then is the bounds of Worldly Love and Friendſhip; It is therefore very unreaſonable, to place our Confidence in theſe things; but let us rather put our Truſt in thoſe, which may be uſeful to us even after we are dead.</p>
               <p>Think how horrid and noiſom the ſtink of thy Carkaſs would be, even to thy neareſt Kindred, and yet this is that Body, for the indulging whereof, thou haſt ſo often offended thy God: How much pains do ſome Men take, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Difficulties do they Encounter with, that they may leave a Rich and Pleaſant Inheritance to their Children? Tho' ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times in the getting of it, they do ſuch unjuſt and wicked Actions, as are never to be purg'd away, but in the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Flames of Hell: And what do they keep to themſelves, as the reward of all their Labours? Nothing but a Deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63173:13"/>Winding-Sheet, and a Coffin made up of four Boards; this is the Recompence of all their Toil: But if ſomething more be ſpent at thy Funeral, it is commonly laid out more for the Fame and Credit of thy Kindred, and the Surviving Heir, than for thee, ſo that a farthing ſhould not ſometimes be beſtowed upon the dead Corps, if they could but ſecure their own Honour.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O Merciful Father, give me ſuch Courage and Reſolution, that I may not be affrighted at the ghaſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Death, nor faint when I think on my laſt dying Agonies, and that my Body muſt rot in the Earth: But ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving my mind fix'd on thee, and on the Glories of the Eternal State, I may put off all fear of Death, and depart this Life with Joy and Readineſs, with a firm hope of a Glorious Reſurrection, and of enjoying that Bliſs and Glory, with which both Body and Soul, ſhall be endued in the Celeſtial and Happy Life. And becauſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63173:14"/>I came naked into this World, let me wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly leave all Worldly things, which may retard my flight to Heaven: O Lord Jeſu, who for our ſakes, didſt taſte the bitterneſs of Death, and in thoſe Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Mind, didſt ſweat great drops of blood; grant that by the Merits of thy Paſſion, I may never feel the bitter pangs of Eternal Death:</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>After Death there remains another Life, and Death is the entrance, either to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Happineſs or Miſery.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALthough the Body after Death cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts and putrifies, and returns to the Earth from whence it was taken; yet for as much as the Soul is immortal, and the Body ſhall ariſe at the laſt Day, and be again united to the Soul, and ſo the whole Man ſhall be tranſlated into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther State: It is therefore requiſite, that a Chriſtian ſhould not confine his Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63173:14"/>upon death only, but ſhould be very Solicitous, that his Life may be happy in the other World: Many Men indeed lead ſuch Lives, as if they did not believe there were a God, nor any other life af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this; but when they come to dye, they will be convinced of theſe truths by their own Conſciences, and by thoſe notions which are implanted in the minds of all Men, that good Deeds ſhall be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, and Wickedneſs puniſhed in the other World; and though they ſhould not believe this, even when they are dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet afterwards they will feel it, to their unſpeakable Sorrow: However the immortality of the Soul has been believed by the whole Race of Mankind at all times; and if we Conſult either Sacred or Heathen Writers, we ſhall find that another life after this, hath been aſſerted by all; not to heap up the many Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of Holy Scriptures, this one of our Saviour may ſuffice, which Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends as it were the Sum of all the reſt; <hi>The Hour is coming,
<note place="margin">Joh. 5.28.</note> in the which all that are in the Graves, ſhall hear the Voice</hi> [<hi>of the Son of God,</hi> v. 25.] <hi>And ſhall come forth, they that have done good unto the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Life; and they that have done Evil, unto the Reſurrection of Damnation.</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:63173:15"/>And indeed if we conſider the lives of thoſe Perſons, which the Sacred Scriptures affirm to have liv'd devoutly, from hence we may have an evident Teſtimony of a future Life, for in all Ages, how much Miſery have they undergone, who have endeavoured to lead Pious Lives, and to be conformable to the Divine Will; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Remarkable are the Calamities of the Holy Fathers under the Old Teſtament; the Martyrdoms of Chriſts Apoſtles under the New, and the Tribulations of others, who have Worſhipp'd God in Spirit and in Truth: But if they had look'd no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than this Life, no doubt but they would have follow'd the common way of the World, and have indulged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Eaſe and Pleaſures, as their Luſts and Appetites bid them: Which ſince they did not do, it is a convincing Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that they ſought a more happy and a better Life after the Miſeries of this: For as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.19.</note> 
                  <hi>If in this Life only we have hope in Chriſt, we are of all Men moſt miſerable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if we Conſult the Heathens, as often as we hear them commend Piety and Juſtice, and other Virtues, ſo often we are to think they declare Mans Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and a Future Life; for to what purpoſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63173:15"/>were it, to follow Virtue, and ſuffer Evil, if there remain'd no hopes of another life: This Doctrine the Wiſe Men in all Ages taught, <hi>Zoroaſter, Hermes, Triſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtus, Orpheus, Phocylides, Theogenis, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Heſiod, Pindar, Pythagoras, Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Plato, Ariſtotle, Cicero, Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil, Horace, Ovid, Seneca,</hi> and all the Wiſe Famous Philoſophers; and from hence it was, that all Nations had a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and certain Rites whereby they worſhipp'd the Gods, and believ'd a Hell and <hi>Elyſian</hi> fields: If we run over the whole World, we ſhall find that the moſt Rude, Barbarous and Savage People, even thoſe who ſcarcely ſeem to have any Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity in them, have all by a common conſent embraced this Faith; for this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was not bred in the Schools of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, and ſo ſpread abroad in the World, but it is implanted and engraven in the Breaſt of every Man;
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.14.25.</note> and if ſome Men have endeavoured to perſwade themſelves that things are otherwiſe, yet could they never bring their minds firmly to believe ſo; for a wicked Man as that <hi>Platonick</hi> ſaid, would not have his Soul to be Immortal, for fear he ſhould ſuffer the due Puniſhments of his Crimes; but he prevents the Sentence of his Judge,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63173:16"/>and condemns himſelf to be guilty of Death: But there is no need of ſaying more on this Argument, ſince amongſt Chriſtians, tis certain and undoubted, that after this life, there remains another.</p>
               <p>But foraſmuch as the future State of Men after this life is not alike, but ſome ſhall abound with all felicity, whilſt others ſhall ſuffer all kind of miſeries: hence we ſee that the ſucceſs of a Man's happineſs depends upon his death, and that all our felicity or infelicity happens either from a good or a bad death; and that on one moment depends an Eternity either of infinite bleſſedneſs, or unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able miſery: for in what ever condition death finds and leaves any Man, in the very ſame ſhall he appear at the laſt judgment,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 11.3.</note> 
                  <hi>if the tree fall toward the South, or toward the North, in the place where the tree falleth, there it ſhall be.</hi> And thus as every Man dies, the ſame ſhall he be in the other life: for as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>we muſt all appear before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.10.</note> that every one may receive the things done in his body, according to that he hath done, whether it be good or bad,</hi> ſo that as every one is found at the hour of death, ſuch ſhall he be judged: They ſhall live happily in the other World,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63173:16"/>that die well: they miſerably, that die ill: And thus it is that the hour of death ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parates the good from the wicked at the greateſt diſtance. To the good death is the end and determination of all troubles, and the beginning of Eternal Felicity and Bleſſedneſs: but to the wicked death is the privation of all the delights, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and riches of this life; and is the beginning of Eternal Miſery, and never ending Puniſhment.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O Merciful Father who didſt create me for a far more bleſſed condition then this miſerable life which the brute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimals enjoy, vouchſafe ſo to direct me in my paſſage through this World, that I may</hi> never ſet my affections on things below; <hi>but uſe them with ſuch indifferency, that I may at length attain to the joys and glories of the bleſſed life above; and that knowing</hi> I have here no continuing City, I may with the greater earneſtneſs ſeek one to come, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13, 14.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:63173:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>The Conſideration of the laſt Judgement.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AFter Death comes Judgment:</hi> Think therefore O Man, that immediately after Death thy Soul muſt appear before God,
<note place="margin">Ecc. 12.7.</note> and that at the laſt Day it ſhall be joyned again to thy body, and then thou ſhalt be Judged before Gods Tribunal, in the preſence of all the Angels and Saints: Conſider that thou muſt appear before a Judge, whoſe unerring Wildom thou canſt by no means deceive, whoſe power thou canſt by no ways avoid, whoſe Juſtice thou canſt by no means corrupt: A Judge who will enquire into thy vaineſt words, and thy moſt trivial thoughts, who is now preſent at, and beholds all the words and actions of the whole World: Who is there ſo bold, ſo deſperately wicked, that dares contumaciouſly violate the Laws, and commit Crimes worthy of Death, in the preſence of his King? And yet more than this dare Men do, who ſpightfully break the Commands of God before his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63173:17"/>face; but this Judge, who knows all our actions,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 12.14. Rom. 14.12.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall bring every work into judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with every ſecret thing, whether it be good or whether it be evil: ſo that every one of us ſhall give an account of himſelf to God: For he which is Lord over all,
<note place="margin">Wiſd. 6.7.</note> ſhall fear no mans perſon, neither ſhall he ſtand in awe of any mans greatneſs; for he hath made the ſmall and great, and careth for all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</hi> Let therefore your thoughts be always employ'd in meditating on this ſevere Judgement, in which there will be no more place for pardon; nothing ſhall then be granted either by Prayers or Tears; but either this merciful Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ſhall paſs on the Righteous,
<note place="margin">Matth. 25.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Well done good and faithful Servant, thou haſt been faithful over a few things, I will make thee ruler over many things: enter thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the joy of thy Lord.
<note place="margin">Ver. 34.</note> Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you from the Foundation of the World:</hi> or on the contrary this terrible Sentence ſhall be thundred out againſt the wicked by the moſt juſt Judge,
<note place="margin">Ver. 41.</note> 
                  <hi>Depart from me, ye curſed, into everlaſting fire prepared for the Devil and his Angels:</hi> What can our minds conceive more ſweet and pleaſant, than to hear God ſaying to us, <hi>come ye bleſſed?</hi> what more ſad and dreadful, than
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63173:18"/>
                  <hi>depart from me, ye curſed, into everlaſting fire:</hi> In this day of Judgement, wealth will not help the rich, nor power, nor honours the great Ones of this World: Knowledge will not abſolve the wiſe, nor will force preſerve the ſtrong: This Judge will not be pleaſed by flatteries, nor brib'd by rewards; no Prayers will move him, no Tears will appeaſe him;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.8.</note> 
                  <hi>but he ſhall judge the World in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and ſhall miniſter judgement to the People in uprightneſs: Then</hi> (as 'tis ſaid in Wiſdom) <hi>ſhall the righteous man ſtand in great boldneſs,
<note place="margin">Chap. 5.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> before the face of ſuch as have afflicted him, and made no account of his labours; when they ſee it they ſhall be troubled with terrible fear, and ſhall be amazed at the ſtrangeneſs of his ſalvation, ſo far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all that they looked for. And they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting and groaning for anguiſh of ſpirit, ſhall ſay within themſelves: This was he whom we had ſometimes in deriſion, and a proverb of reproach. We fools accounted his life madneſs, and his end to be without honour. How is he numbred among the Children of God, and his lot is among the Saints!</hi> Conſider farther, O man, who they are that in this future Judgement ſhall hear this joyful word, <hi>come ye bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> and ſhall be made partakers of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63173:18"/>Glory; and on the contrary, who they are, on whom this dreadful Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ſhall be pronounced, <hi>depart from me ye curſed;</hi> and ſo ſhall be caſt into Hell fire; and then give all diligence that you may be found in the number of the bleſſed, and not amongſt the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: Now, who both theſe are, the Holy Scriptures do ſufficiently declare: Our Saviour himſelf tells us,
<note place="margin">Mat. 13.41.</note> 
                  <hi>that the Angels ſhall gather the wicked together, and caſt them into a furnace of fire:
<note place="margin">John 3.36.</note> He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth not the Son, ſhall not ſee life, but the wrath of God abideth on him:
<note place="margin">John 3.19.</note> And this is the Condemnation, that light is come into the World, and men loved darkneſs rather than light, becauſe their deeds were evil: But the fearful and unbelieving,
<note place="margin">Rez. 21.8.</note> and the abominable, and murderers, and whoremongers, and ſorcerers, and idolaters, and all liars ſhall have their part in the Lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone; which is the ſecond death:
<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.7, 8, 9.</note> The Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from Heaven, with his mighty Angels, in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: Who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction from the preſence of the Lord: Know ye not that the unrighteous ſhall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.9, 10.</note>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:63173:19"/>the Kingdom of God: be not deceived: neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, nor effeminate, nor abuſers of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with monkind. nor thieves, nor cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioners, ſhall inherit the Kindom of God. Now the works of the fleſh are manifeſt, which are theſe;
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.19, 20, 21.</note> adultery, fornication, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, laſciviouſneſs, idolatry, witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, hatred, variance, emulations, wrath, strife, ſeditions, hereſies, envyings, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, drunkenneſs, revellings, and ſuch like, of the which I tell you before, as I have alſo told you in time paſt, that they which do ſuch things, ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God:</hi> On the contrary we are told, who they are that ſhall be ſav'd.
<note place="margin">Joh. 3.18. Mark 16.16. Rom. 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>He that believeth on the Son of God, is not condemned: He that believeth, and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being juſtified by Faith, we have peace with God, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LOrd Jeſu Chriſt, guide me by thy Holy Spirit, that I may walk in thy ways; and always have in my
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63173:19"/>mind this ſum of the</hi> whole Duty of Man:
<note place="margin">Eccl. 12.13, 14.</note> fear God and keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments: For God ſhall bring every work into Judgement, with every ſecret thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil. <hi>O let every moment that voice ſound in mine ears:</hi> ariſe ye dead, and come to judgement. <hi>And at the laſt let me hear thy gracious voice ſaying,</hi> come thou bleſſed of my Father inherit the Kingdom prepared for thee from the beginning of the World. <hi>I acknowledge indeed and confeſs, that by my ſins I have deſerved the pains of Hell: but thou by thy Paſſion, Death, and Reſurrection haſt redeemed me from them, and merited Heaven for me: In thee therefore, in thy merits and mercies I put my whole truſt and confidence, and joyfully expect thy glorious coming,</hi> Amen: Come Lord Jeſus, Amen. <hi>Rev.</hi> XXII. 20.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:63173:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>The Joys of the Life eternal.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALthough it cannot be imagin'd, much leſs expreſs'd in words, what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference there is between the joys of Heaven, and the pains and miſeries of the damned; yet for as much as many live as if it matter'd little or nothing, whether after death they were to be admitted into the bleſſed Life above, or to be caſt into the bottomleſs pit: it therefore well becomes a Chriſtian daily to conſider, how vaſtly the miſeries of Hell differ from the glories of Heaven, that ſo he may be convinced how neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary it is earneſtly to endeavour to avoid the one and obtain the other: For who is there ſo void of ſence, that for the hopes of gaining one Farthing, would run the hazard of loſing an hundred thouſand Crowns? and yet this they daily do, who defile themſelves with ſin, that they may follow after the riches, pleaſures, and honours of this World: for all theſe things, and even the whole World (could any man gain it to himſelf,) are more
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63173:20"/>vile, if they be compared to eternal liſe, (which is utterly loſt by ſin) than the ſmalleſt mite compar'd to the greateſt ſum imaginable: Or who is there ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately wicked that would dare to commit crimes worthy of death, in the ſight of a Gibbet, a drawn Sword, or a flaming fire, and in the preſence of a Judge, who he knew would immediately condemn him to theſe torments; and yet this they do, who well knowing that the pains of Hell are ſo plainly ſet before their eyes in the Holy Scriptures, do yet daily commit ſuch ſins, as juſtly deſerve thoſe infernal plagues.</p>
               <p>Now eternal Happineſs conſiſts in theſe two things: In the abſence of all evil things, and in the enjoyment of every thing that is good:
<note place="margin">Rev. 21.4.</note> 
                  <hi>For God ſhall wipe away all tears from the eyes of</hi> the bleſſed, <hi>and there ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrow nor crying, neither ſhall there be any more pain:</hi> And, <hi>as it is written,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9.</note> eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, neither have entred into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him:</hi> For what greater felicity can there be than to have no calamities to diſturb us, not to be terrified with the fear of death, to behold the face of God, to be amongſt the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63173:21"/>Quires of Angels, to ſerve our Creatour with the bleſſed Spirits, and all the Saints; and with perpetual Hyms and Praiſes to magnifie his glorious Name? If you value and deſire Health, there ſhall be conſtant ſoundneſs and eternal Life: If you are delighted with the friendſhip of good men, there you ſhall have the familiar acquaintance of all the bleſſed inhabitants above, who will all have one Heart and one Soul: In ſhort; there will be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wanting that a man can wiſh for. <hi>What</hi> (ſaith St.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quid, inquit</hi> Auguſtinus, <hi>hac vita beatius, ubi non eſt paupertatis metus, non agritudinis imbectllitas? nemo laeditur, nemo iraſcitur, nemo invidet, cupiditas nulla exardeſcit, nullum cibi deſiderium, nulla honoris, aut poteſtatis pulſat ambitio, nullus Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aboli metus, inſidia Daemonum nulla, terror gehennae pracul, mors neque cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris neque animae, ſed immortalitatis munere jucunda vita. Nulla ibi diſcordia, cuncta conſona, cuncta con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venientia, Sanctorum omnium una erit concordia. Nox ibi nulla, nullae tenebrae; ſed lux ſumma: quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam Dominus inluminabit civitatem, &amp; Incerna ejus erit Agnus &amp; Sancti fulgebunt ſicut ſtellae &amp; ſicut ſplendor firmamenti. Dabitur ibi conſociare choris Angelorum, intueri Patriarchas &amp; Prophetas, videre Apoſtolos atque omnes Sanctos. Glorioſa ſunt hac ſed multo gloriſius erit D E <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> M intueri.</hi> Manual. cap. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtin</hi>) <hi>can be more happy than this life, where there is no fear of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, nor the weakneſs of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities? no body is hurt, no body is angry: none envies another: no luſt inflames them no longing after food; no deſire of honour and power diſquiets them: there is no dread of Satan, no ſnares of the Devil, no fear of Hell: there is neither death of Body or Soul, but by the means of immertality a most delightful life: there will be no evil, no diſcord, but a perfect harmony, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63173:21"/>there will be a mutual agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween all the Saints: there will be no night, nor darkneſs, but the greateſt light, for the Glory of God will enlighten it,
<note place="margin">Rev. 21.23.</note> and the Lamb will be the light thereof,
<note place="margin">Dan. 12.3.</note> and the Saints ſhall ſhine as the Stars, and as the brightneſs of the Firmament: there we ſhall aſſociate with the multitudes of Angels and Archangels, and all the Heavenly Powers; there we ſhall behold the Patriarchs and Prophets, the Apoſtles and all the Saints: theſe are glorious things, but it will be yet much more glorious to behold GOD himſelf:</hi> for the happineſs and glory of eternal life doth chiefly conſiſt in the viſion and enjoyment of God, who will then be all in all. But how great this future felicity will be, the mind of man is not capable to conceive: however we may make ſome faint conjectures: for ſeeing God is the Creatour and Preſerver of all things, it muſt needs be that all the things in the World which to us appear fair and beautiful, are in him ſo, much more eminently: if therefore the proſpect and contemplation of the Creatures be ſweet and grateful, the Creatour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf muſt needs be much more raviſhing and delightful: ſo that ſince we ſhall ſee God face to face, all, even the moſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63173:22"/>beautiful things in this World, will be ſurmounted by the tranſcendent beauty of God: He ſhall be <hi>all in all,</hi> the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of all deſires, and the perfect fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity of the Saints:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are they that dwell in thy Houſe, they will always be praiſing thee:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.19.</note> O how great is thy Goodneſs, which thou hast laid up for them that fear thee!</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ALmighty Lord God, foraſmuch as eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, neither hath it entred into the Heart of Man to conceive thoſe good things which thou haſt prepar'd for thoſe that love thee; I muſt needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that through the dullneſs of my Senſes, which cannot comprehend theſe things, I have not ſo earneſtly ſought after eternal life as I ought to have done: Vouchſafe therefore to illuminate my mind, that I may in ſome meaſure underſtand the Excellency of Heaven; that my Soul may long after its joys, and being capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63173:22"/>therewith, I may deſpiſe this World, and value it as nothing in compariſon of the Glories of that bleſſed and eternal Life: ſo direct all my thoughts and actions that I may at length attain to that bleſſed and happy State, where no miſery nor ſorrow dwells; that I may ſee thee face to face with all thy Saints, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the full poſſeſsion of thoſe immenſe glories and felicitlites, which are at thy right hand for evermore,</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:63173:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>The pains and miſeries of Hell.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AND now ſhould there be any one ſo deteſtably wicked as not to be allured by the happineſs of eternal life; yet ſurely the miſeries of Hell would terrifie him: Now Hell in holy Writ is call'd <hi>a furnace of fire:
<note place="margin">Mat. 13.42.</note> eternal fire: and that cannot be quenched:
<note place="margin">Mat. 25.46.</note> an everlaſting puniſhment:
<note place="margin">Apoc. 9.</note> destruction: the bottomlejs pit: outer darkneſs,
<note place="margin">Mat. 8.12.</note> where ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth:
<note place="margin">Mat. 25.41.</note> everlaſting fire prepared for the Devil and his Angels:
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> tribulation and anguiſh:
<note place="margin">Apoc. 21.8.</note> a Lake that burns with fire and brimſtone.</hi> All which names of Hell admoniſh us, that the pains of the damned ſhall be eternal, moſt grievous, infinite, inexpreſſible, and accompanied with the Society of Devils. As to the eternity thereof (which is the longeſt, and alſo endureth the long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt) pious Antiquity hath illuſtrated it with ſuch ſimilitudes as theſe: ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe there were a Mountain of Sand heap'd up to Heaven, and that once in a thouſand years a little Bird ſhould
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63173:23"/>take from thence one grain of ſand: there would be hopes that after many million of years, and a long ſpace of time that can ſcarcely be conceived, the Mountain would at laſt be conſumed; but in eternity no ſuch thing can be hop'd for: Or, ſuppoſe a ſcrol of Parchment ſo long as to encompaſs the whole Globe of the Earth, nay even the higheſt Sphere of Heaven, on which ſhould be written nothing but cloſely joyned Figures of Nine throughout; now tho' no Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metician can compute this number, yet doth it not by far reach eternity: and ſhould you add a thouſand more, nay, a thouſand thouſand of the like numbers, yet could you by no means comprehend eternity; ſince then eternity is ſo unmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurably long, certainly none but men that are deſperate, can be careleſs and negligent how they are to ſpend it, or rather ſince it can never be ſpent, not to conſider whether they ſhall be happy or miſerable in the other World: What madneſs is it, for trifles and things of no value to be caſt headlong into Hell, there to be puniſhed with unſpeakable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for ever and ever? Should any one bring you to a furious flaming fire, and there ask you, for what price, or for what
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63173:24"/>part of voluptuouſneſs, you would be willing to be tormented in it, for a day, or for but one hour? would you not eaſily anſwer him, that you would not buy ſuch tortures, for all the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures the Earth affords, no nor for all the World? how then is it, that for ſome petty-gain, ſome deceitful honour, ſome flitting ſhort-liv'd pleaſure, you chooſe to burn in the eternal flames of Hell? you are afraid of the fire for an hour, though you ſhould gain the whole World, and yet you caſt your ſelf into the eternal torments of Hell, for things of no value:
<note place="margin">De reparat. lapſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Tell me,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Chryſoſtome, how long a ſeaſon of luxurr, how much vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſneſs, would you ſet againſt eternal torments? an hundred years, we will give to pleaſures, and an hundred more, and if you pleaſe, a thouſand more: alas! what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation is this for eternity? is not all the time of our life, which we ſpend in pleaſure and luxury, like the vain dream of one night, if it be compar'd to eternity? is there then any one, who for a pleaſing dream one night, would chooſe to undergo eternal torments? and be willing to receive theſe, ſo he might but enjoy that? Pleaſures paſs away like a ſhadow, but the puniſhments re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main without end; and although the ſame
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63173:24"/>ſpace of time were allotted for the delights of this World, and the pains of Hell, yet is there any one ſo fooliſh and void of Senſe, that would chooſe to Juffer one days Infernal Plagues, for one days Worldly Pleaſure? When as one hours pain, any Torment of the Body is wont to make us forget all the time paſt of our Lives, which we have ſpent in pleaſures:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor are the pains of Hell only Eternal, but alſo infinitely grievous and inexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: For nothing ſo ſad or terrible can be imagined, but thoſe Eternal Torments are ſtill more grievous; All the moſt dreadful, inhumane, and cruel things which the Barbarity of Tyrants have ever invented, are not to be compared with theſe pains of Hell: For not only the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but the Soul alſo ſhall be afflicted: The remembrance of paſt offences, which have occaſion'd ſo many Evils, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual ſence of Racking Pains, the Hatred and Deteſtation of God and all the Saints, and principally the thoughts of being for ever rejected from the moſt bliſsful ſight of God; all theſe things do miſerably torment the Sinner: There will be heard the doleful Cries, Sighs and Lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Curſings and Execrations of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, Children, Brethren, Siſters, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63173:25"/>Friends, who by their Example or Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, have thrown others into that place of Torments; for they will be moſt furiouſly enraged againſt thoſe whom above all others in this life they loved moſt dearly: At the ſight of them, they ſhall be provoked and incenſed, as againſt their greateſt enemies.</p>
               <p>And now though theſe Torments are of themſelves very ſad and terrible, yet are they ſtill made more grievous by the perpetual Society of Devils and damned Spirits. Any one that has ſeen a Man poſſeſſed with the Devil, or if he hath not ſeen one, yet hath read out of the Goſpel or other Hiſtories, the deplorable condition of thoſe men that are poſſeſs'd; will eaſily believe what a moſt woful thing it is to be under the power of the Devil. Who is there of ſo undaunted a Courage, that is not afraid of Appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are diſguiſed Devils, and does not tremble at the ſight of them: And yet the Devil in poſſeſs'd folks, or when he terrifies Men by his Evil Spirits, hath no more power over Men, than God is pleas'd to grant him, and hath not yet a full Dominion over them: But in Hell, where the Damned are delivered up by God to be Tormented, he uſeth his own
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63173:25"/>Liberty and Authority, and exerciſes ſuch Cruelty on them, as the mind of Man is not capable to conceive: Think then, O Man, how great their Miſery ſhall be, who muſt live in the Society, and under the Dominion of Devils, and undergo their Rage and Malice to Eternal Ages: Think, O Man, what great Miſery it would be, to be ſhut up in a cloſe Room for a Month together with Mad folks, or ſuch as are poſſeſs'd, and from thence you may Conjecture, how wretched their condition will be, who muſt be forc'd to live with many Myriads of outragious Devils to all Eternity: Oh! How will the Devils Tyrannize, not only over the meaner and baſer rank of Men, but alſo over Emperours, Kings and Princes, thoſe of the higheſt Order and Quality! How will the Great Ones of this World be great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tormented and plagued by the Devils, and ſcoffed at with biting Taunts and Jeers! After the ſame manner will they inſult over all ranks of Men, and will as much as they can, increaſe their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by Revilings, Reproaches and Mockings; they will laugh at, and make a jeſt of the Damned, that they ſhould precipitate themſelves into the Lake of Fire and Brimſtone for trifles, for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63173:26"/>Honours, decaying Riches, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Pleaſures, or vain Joys; and that they ſhould ſooner believe them, who they knew were their ſworn Enemies, than the great and good God the Maker, and Redeemer of Mankind.</p>
               <p>And then laſtly, there is not only the Society of Devils, but alſo of the Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which will ſtill farther aggravate their Puniſhment: Nothing will there be ſeen, but the Eternal and Horrid Plagues and Tortures of the Damned Fiends, nothing will there be heard, but Stripes and Wailings, Curſes and Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of thoſe who by Counſel, Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Example, were the cauſes and occaſions of their ſinning; and more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable will be the Expoſtulations of Parents with their Children, that for their ſakes they were caſt into theſe Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whilſt they endeavoured by all means right or wrong, to heap up Riches and Wealth for them; and on the other ſide, the Children will accuſe their Parents, and impute the cauſe of their Damnation to them, that by their Examples or Indulgency, they gave them the occaſions of Sinning.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:63173:26"/>
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OLord Jeſus Chriſt, guide and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate my mind, that I may daily remember, and attentively conſider, what a vaſt difference there is between the Joys of Eternal Life, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of Hell: And direct me by thy Holy Spirit in the ways of thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that I may walk in that narrow Path that leadeth unto Life; and ſuffer me not to be ſeduced by Satan into the broad way of the Wicked, which leadeth to Deſtruction, leaſt I fall headlong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Lake of Fire and Brimſtone, from which thou haſt Redeemed me by thy moſt precious Blood; but by the Efficacy of thy Merits, let me live with Thee for ever and ever in Heaven.</hi> Amen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Who amongſt us can dwell with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring fire?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Who amongſt us can dwell with everlasting burnings?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:63173:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>To die well there is great need of a careful Preparation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SInce then there is ſo great a difference between that Bleſſed Life above, and the Miſeries of the Damned; that death is the paſſage either to Eternal Blifs or Puniſhment; and that the everlaſting Happineſs or Miſery of all Men, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on one Moment, that bleſſed are the dead that die in the Lord: but for ever miſerable are they, that die the death of the Wicked: And that our Eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation depends upon an happy death: It certainly ought to be our chiefeſt care and concern to learn to die well, and to prepare ourſelves aright for an happy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture: Now he dies well, who hath liv'd well, and whom Death doth not find unprovided:
<note place="margin">De diſcipl. Eccl. cap. 2.</note> For, as St. <hi>Augustin</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Non enim poteſt male mori, qui bone vixerit.</note> 
                  <hi>it is not poſſible for him to die ill, who hath liv'd well:</hi> But great need there is of preparation for any one to die well: For if we never undertake any matter of ſmall importance, as the going of a Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63173:27"/>or the like, without ſome proviſion, and often thinking on it before-hand; it certainly is much more neceſſary to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Solicitous, and attentively to conſider after what manner we are to demean our ſelves at the hour of Death, that ſo we may obtain the Felicity of Eternal Life, and avoid the Pains and Miſeries of Hell.</p>
               <p>Now the preparation for Death is Two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold: The one General, and to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed every day: The other Special, and is neceſſary when Death approaches.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OLord God and moſt Merciful Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for as much as my Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion depends upon an happy death, do thou vouchſafe ſo to direct my mind, that I may be always very careful how to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to my ſelf an happy paſſage out of this World, and ſo to order my ſelf and all that belongs unto me, that at what ever hour thou ſhalt pleaſe to call me hence, I may be found ready, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63173:28"/>through the gate of Death, I may be Tranſlated into thy Glorious Kingdom, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>The general and daily Preparation for Death: The firſt Conſideration, that Death is certain, Life is ſhort, and the hour of Death is uncertain.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE general and daily Preparation for Death, we ſhall treat of in the following Chapters, deſiring the devout Chriſtian to conſider: 1ſt. That death is certain, life ſhort, and the hour of death uncertain: 2ly. That death is not to be feared: And 3ly. the Chriſtian Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that are daily to be performed by him:</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt. Then it is fitting for a Man that intends to die well, often to ponder in his mind the certainty of Death, the ſhortneſs of Human Life, and the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the hour of Death.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:63173:28"/>
               <p>For in the firſt place the continual Meditation of our Mortality, may be a very effectual means to prepare us both to live and to die well; nothing can better ſhew us the way of holy living, no exhortation to piety and vertue more prevalent than the remembrance of death; nothing more powerfully calls us off from our ſins, and from a fond deſire after worldly things, than the ſerious conſideration of the frailty, inſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and approaching diſſolution of our bodies: for as that laſt moment of our lives will take off all the ſalſe colours and diſguiſes from earthly things, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them clearly to our view, as they are in themſelves, vain and deſpicable; ſo the frequent premeditation of that hour quickens the ſight of our minds more plainly to perceive the ſame Truths; for whilſt our minds are full of the thoughts of our mortality, thoſe things which follow after death will preſently inſinuate themſelves; then will ſinners ſee Hell open before them, and the unquenchable fire ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour them, which will ſo terrifie their conſciences, that neither honours, nor riches, nor pleaſures, nor any other worldly thing can any longer pleaſe or entice them.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:63173:29"/>
               <p>And as nothing is more profitable for us, than the daily meditation of death, ſo on the contrary nothing is more hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, than our forgetfulneſs of it; and yet this is very common with the rich Men and great Ones of this World, who, as if they were to live the age of <hi>Methuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lah,</hi> lay up Proviſions for many years continuance here, and in the mean time think little or nothing of the life to come; and ſo when they fancy they have attained to the top of their deſires, on a ſudden, with the rich Man in the Goſpel, they are forced to depart out of this life, and too often deſcend into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal deſtruction: and foraſmuch as the Devil well knows, that nothing more powerfully excites men to holineſs or better ſecures their ſouls from his ſnares, than the meditation of death, he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore employs his greateſt care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to put theſe thoughts out of mens minds; which if he can but obtain, he eaſily gets every thing elſe he has a mind to, and takes men captive at his will: It is a ſign of a mind altogether deprav'd, and out of order, which doth not care to hear Diſcourſes and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of Death, which is ſad and uneaſie at the thoughts of it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63173:29"/>ſtrives to divert it ſelf with witty ſayings and merriment, with full bowls and all kinds of delight and paſtime: But on the contrary, he who is in favour with God, whoſe Soul is not plunged in ſenſual pleaſures, it is his delight to think often and to diſcourſe of death, for he knows 'tis the only neceſſary way to everlaſting bliſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Towards our preparation for death, we are to conſider <hi>the ſhortneſs of our lives;</hi> for how little time doth God allow us to live here? many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants expire at their very entrance in to life; ſome die in their Childhood, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in their Youth; fewer arrive to their middle age; but very few attain to old age: from hence it is that in Holy Scripture our life is compar'd to thoſe things that are moſt frail and momentary: as <hi>the trace of a cloud, a miſt, a ſpark,
<note place="margin">Wiſd. 2. Job. 14.2. Pſal. 90. Job. 5.6.9.</note> a ſhadow, a flower, a weavers ſhuttle, a poſt, a ſwift ſhip, and an eagle that haſteth to his prey:</hi> This alſo the Heathen declar'd, and therefore <hi>Pindar</hi> call'd man, <hi>the dream of a ſhadow,</hi> Aeſchylus, <hi>the ſhadow of ſmoke;</hi> M. Varro, <hi>a bubble:</hi> and with good reaſon are theſe names attributed to man; for we die daily, and ſome part of our lives are every day taken from us; our whole
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:63173:30"/>ſtate is nothing elſe but a journey, a race to death.</p>
               <p>And then, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſider that in this ſhort life the time of death is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; for tho' it is appointed for all to die, yet the hour of death is unknown: ſome die in their Infancy, ſome in their Youth, and ſome in their old Age, whilſt others are overtaken by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected death, ſo that no one can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure himſelf of to morrow; neither is the place or manner of our death known to us, which is daily confirm'd to us by the dead Corpſes we ſee carried by: For all that die do not keep their Beds, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted by a long continued ſickneſs; for ſome are taken away ſuddenly, or in a moment loſe their Senſes by Appoplexies; others are choak'd by violent Catarrhs; ſome are kill'd by falls, ſome by the ruins of Houſes, whilſt others are trod under feet by Horſes; ſome are drowned in the Water, and others are ſtruck with Lightning, whilſt others unexpectedly fall into the hands of Thieves and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and come to an untimely end, which they never were afraid of: Now what happens to one, may happen to all; and what may happen to all, every one ought to expect may happen to them:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63173:30"/>
                  <hi>For man alſo knoweth not his time,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.12.</note> as the fiſhes that are taken in an evil net, and as the birds that are caught in the ſnare, ſo are the ſons of men ſnared in an evil time, when it falleth ſuddenly upon them;</hi> being then men, we ought to think that whatever is common to man, and does ſometimes happen to others, may alſo befal us: Now hereby we are admoniſh'd to be every minute ready and prepar'd for death: For God was pleaſed to let us be ignorant of the time of our death, that the uncertainty thereof might be a means of exciting in us a conſtant practice of vertue and avoiding of ſin, and a perpetual care and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſecure our eternal wellfare, for how dangerous is it to live in ſuch a condition, that if a ſudden death ſhould ſurprize us unawares, our ſalvation is utterly to be deſpair'd of? and who can aſcertain us, that at the end of our lives, when death comes on us like an armed man, we ſhall be in ſo good a diſpoſition as to be able to bewail our ſins, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore the grace and mercy of God? Indeed were we permitted to die often, and return again to life, their raſhneſs and ſecurity were excuſable, who ſo ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom think of death; but ſince 'tis ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63173:31"/>unto all men but once to die, and that there is no leading of our lives over again, 'tis manifeſt what great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger they run, whom death overtakes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are provided for it, ſince it for ever takes away from them all hopes of ſalvation: Let us then be always prepared for death, let us fly from ſin, and not defer our repentance, let us not cheriſh anger and revenge, evil affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and a fond deſire of living long in this World; but let us account every day to be our laſt; and when we go to ſleep, let us ſo demean our ſelves, as if we were never to ariſe again from our beds; and when we ariſe in the morning, let us ſo ſpend every hour of the day, as if we were never to lie down in our beds again; let us ſo uſe the good things of this World, as if we were to leave them every moment: let us not vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly promiſe our ſelves along continuance here, with that rich man in the Goſpel, who ſaid unto his Soul,
<note place="margin">Luk. 12.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Soul thou haſt much goods laid up for many years; take thine eaſe, eat, drink, and be merry:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as that very night, his Soul was required of him: but let us daily pray with holy <hi>David,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 39.5.</note> Lord let me know my end and the number of my days, that I may be certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:63173:31"/>how long I have to live;</hi> and let us not neglact that wholſom Admonition of our Saviour, who ſaith:
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.46. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque ad fin.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed is that Servant whom his Lord when he cometh, ſhall find watching; Verily I ſay unto you, that he ſhall make him Ruler over all his Goods: But, and if that Evil Servant ſhall ſay in his Heart, My Lord delayeth his coming, and ſhall begin to ſmite his fellow Servants, and to eat and drink with the Drunken. The Lord of that Servant ſhall come in a day when he looketh not for him, and in an hour that he is not a ware of: And ſhall cut him aſunder, and appoint him his Portion with the Hypocrites: There ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of Teeth;</hi> but let us be wiſe and <hi>faithful Servants, that are always ready, expecting their Lord, for we know not what hour he will come,
<note place="margin">Mark 13.35.</note> whether at even, or at midnight, or at the Cock crowing, or in the morning: Least coming ſuddenly, he find us ſleeping,</hi> and unprepared for him. St. <hi>Augustin</hi> tells us,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In quo enim, quemque invene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſuus noviſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus dies, in hoc eum compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendit mundi noviſſimus dies. St.</hi> Auguſtin. cap. 11.3.</note> 
                  <hi>that in what ever condition our laſt day leaves us, in the ſame state will the last day of the World find us:</hi> For as a Man dies in the one, ſo in the other he ſhall be judged. To this purpoſe that ſaying in <hi>Eccleſiastes</hi> is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally applied, <hi>if the Tree fall toward the</hi> South, <hi>or toward the</hi> North, <hi>in the place
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:63173:32"/>where the Tree falleth,
<note place="margin">Com. Sup. Eccl. cap. 11.</note> there it ſhall be.</hi> This St. <hi>Hierom</hi> thus interprets, that as a Tree certainly lies, which way ſoever it ſalls; ſo when thou art cut off by the ſtroke of Death, thou ſhalt always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſuch, whether your laſt Moment found you Cruel and Unmerciful, or Meek and Charitable. Could any one tell for certain, that he had but one day more to live, and evidently knew that he muſt die to Morrow, ſurely ſuch a Man were extreamly wicked, if he could not, Abſtain from ſin for ſo ſhort a Seaſon, and ſhould not employ all that little ſpace of Life in the Exerciſes of Piety and Virtue, when as that Judgment which is paſſed on us at our Death, ſhall moſt aſſuredly always remain firm and unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable: And who is there can warrant himſelf to morrow? Who is there that knows, as a thing ſure and undoubted, that he hath another day, nay, another hour to live? O Man, whoſoever thou art, there will come an Evening, whole Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or a Morning, whoſe Evening thou ſhalt never ſee; and whether this may not be to day or to morrow, thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not: So that they are without all manner of reaſon, who are not afraid to defile themſelves with deadly ſins, when
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:63173:32"/>they know not whether they ſhall be allowed the ſpace of one hour, of one moment to bewail their Crimes, and beg pardon for them at the hands of God: God hath indeed promiſed Pardon to the Penitent; but he hath never promiſed to the Sinner any portion of the time to come: <hi>Make no tarrying therefore to turn unto the Lord, and put not off from day to day, for ſuddenly ſhall the wrath of the Lord come forth,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 5.8.</note> and in thy ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity thou ſhalt be destroyed, and periſh in the day of vengeance.</hi> This the wiſer Heathen well underſtood, inſomuch that 'tis a ſhame Chriſtians ſhould be out done by them in this matter. For thus <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeaks;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qui ut bonus ſit, in ſenectutem differt, apertè aſtendit, ſe nolle virtuti dare, niſi tempus ad alia omnia inidoneum. Et</hi> alibi <hi>Audies pleroſque dicentes, a quinquageſimo in otium ſecedam, ſex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ageſimus annus ab officiis me dimittet. Et quem tandem longioris vitae praedem accipts? Quis ita, ſicuti diſponis, irae patietur? Non pudet te ad reliquias vitae te tibi reſervare, &amp; id ſelum tempus bonae menti deſtinare, qued in nullam rem conferri poſſit? Quum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt, tunc vivere incipere, cum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnendum eſt? Quae tam ſtulta mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitatis eblivio, in quinquageſitnnm &amp; ſexageſimum annum differre ſana conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, &amp; inde velle vitam inchoare quo pauci perduxerunt? Seneca de Brev. vitae.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>He who deſers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good till old Age, ſhows plainly, that he is loath to give up himſelf to Virtue, until he is fit for nothing elſe.</hi> And in an other place; <hi>you ſhall hear almost every one ſaying, after fifty I ſhall be at leaſure; when I am threeſcore years Old, I ſhall be free from all Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; but what Security have you now for a longer life? Who will undertake
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:63173:33"/>for you, that all things ſhall go juſt as you have order'd them? are you not aſham'd to reſerve your ſelf the reliques of your life for your own good, and ſet a part that time only for wiſdom and goodneſs which is worth nothing? How late is it then to begin your life, when you muſt be forced to leave it? how fooliſh a forgetfulneſs of your mortality is it, to put off all good counſel, till you are fifty or threeſcore years old, and to begin to live at an age to which few arrive?</hi> What penance it is to leave your Harlots, when you are forced to leave them whether you will or no? to begin to be temperate when you can no longer taſte what you eat or what you drink? To this purpoſe ſaith St.
<note place="margin">Maledictus qui florem juventutis diabolo, foces Senectutis DEO conſecrat.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtin</hi> diſcreetly: <hi>Curſed be he that dedicates the flour of his youth to the Devil, and the dregs of old age to God.</hi> When once the laſt moment of our Life is paſt, there is then no longer time for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; and in a little time a Man will be made ſenſible of that State which can never be alter'd to all Eternity: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>whatſoever thou takeſt in hand, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the end,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 7. ult.</note> and thou ſhalt never do amiſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us then every moment be ready to receive the ſummons of death, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring our ſelves for it, whilſt we are
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:63173:33"/>in our health: It is a very unſeaſonable time to begin to fit our ſelves for another World, when we are juſt on the confines of death, and are ſtrugling with the ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of it; for then the lively powers both of mind and body languiſh and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay: then the man is ſo diſtracted with pains, and other grievances, which his ſickneſs occaſions, that he can never ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly apply himſelf to die well: nay, many times a frenzy ſeizes on the ſick perſon, and on a ſudden deprives him of the uſe of all his reaſon: we often ſee that even good men cannot liſt up their thoughts unto God, as they ought, when an acute pain in their teeth, or eyes, or ears, or any other part troubles them, but their whole mind is carried thither where their grief is. Now if this happens to good men, when the diſeaſe is not dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; what can we think ſhall befal thoſe, who never had any ſerious thoughts of God, who know not how to ſearch out, or confeſs their ſins, who can ſcarcely tell what repentance means? how will they be tormented, when the pangs of death are upon them, to conſider that they are now leaving their dear Wife and Children, and that all their riches which they have hoarded up with ſo much
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:63173:34"/>care will now ſtand them in no ſtead? What madneſs then is it to defer a buſineſs of ſuch weighty conſequence, on which our eternal ſalvation depends, to ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper, ſo unfit a time? it is rightly ſaid, that late repentance ſeldom happens to be true and ſerious, and God by a juſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment oftentimes diſregards thoſe when they are dying, who thought it grievous to remember God when they were well in health: Of theſe the Divine Wiſdom thus ſpeaks:
<note place="margin">Prov. 1.24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Becauſe I have called, and ye refuſed, I have ſtretched out my hand, and no man regarded; but ye have ſet at nought all my counſel, and would none of my reproof: I alſo will laugh at your calamity, I will mock when your fear cometh; when your fear com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as deſolation, when diſtreſs and anguiſh come<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h upon you. Then ſhall they call upon me, but I will not anſwer; they ſhall ſeek me early, but they ſhall not find me: For that they hated knowledge, and did not chooſe the fear of the Lord; they would none of my counſel; they deſpiſed all my reproof.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:63173:34"/>
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O Moſt infinite Wiſdom, thy thoughts are not like our thoughts! ſince then it did not pleaſe thee, to reveal un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us the hour of our death, grant, that I may be always prepared for an happy departure hence, that at thy coming, I may be found watching and ready: let not the hour of death ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize me in my ſins, and let me never ſpend one day without true repentance: Inliven my Soul to be perpetually aſpiring after thee, and loving thee, that ſo all things that happen to me, may work to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for good, and nothing may be able to ſeparate me from the love of Chriſt Jeſus thy Son our Lord,</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:63173:35"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>That Death is not to be fear'd.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SInce then it is certain that all muſt die, that life is ſhort, and the hour of death is uncertain, and that therefore it becomes us to be every moment prepared for an happy departure hence, unleſs we will run the hazard of loſing our Souls for ever: the devout Chriſtian therefore may prepare himſelf to die well, if in the ſecond place he learns not to fear death: This then is the ſecond head of thoſe general and daily preparations for a bleſſed death, that we bear the thoughts of death with a couragious mind, and that we never be captivated with the falſe pleaſures of life, and the fond deſire after earthly things: for the pleaſures of life, and the blandiſhments of this World, are chiefly to be reckon'd amongſt thoſe things which make death moſt bitter and formidable to us: We know no union more cloſe than that of Soul and Body, ſo that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:63173:35"/>nothing can appear more terrible than death, which ſeparates Soul and Body, thoſe two intimate companions: more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over in this life, there are many things we much value, and which engage our affections to them: ſuch as are, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Buildings, ſumptuous Apparel, Veſſels of Gold and Silver, Riches, fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Fields, delightful Gardens, pleaſant Vineyards, Parents, Children, Wife, and Friends, of all which ſince death bereaves us, 'tis no wonder if we account it bitter: Hence 'tis ſaid in <hi>Eccleſiaſticus:
<note place="margin">Cap. 41.1.</note> O death how bitter is the remembrance of thee, to a man that liveth at reſt in his poſſeſſions, unto the man that hath nothing to vex him, and that hath proſperity in all things:</hi> But now a diligent conſideration of the miſeries and troubles of this life, of which we ſhall ſpeak by and by; and of the joys of eternal life, of which we have before treated, will ſoon root out of our hearts all fondneſs and complacency for earthly things; for theſe pleaſures are falſe and counterfeit; and under the ſweet lies gall and bitterneſs: This made <hi>Solomon,</hi> the wiſeſt of Kings, who wanted nothing this Wotld could af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford to make his life happy, upon his own experience, ſay, that all things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:63173:36"/>the Sun are vain and empty: <hi>Vanity of Vanities,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 1.2.</note> all is Vanity:</hi> In this World we live like Strangers and Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims, why then do we not deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into our own Countrey? what ever we leave behind us here, ſhall there be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced with far more Excellent and Tranſcendent Rewards? Thus our Saviour adviſeth us:
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Lay not up for your ſelves treaſures upon Earth, where moth and ruſt doth corrupt, and where thieves break through and ſteal: But lay up for your ſelves treaſures in Heaven, where neither moth nor ruſt doth corrupt, and where thieves do not break through nor ſteal.</hi> Altho' many things here are pleaſant and grateful to us yet compar'd to Eternal Life they are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be accounted off: when we die we do not loſe all thoſe faithful Servants of Chriſt, which were here ſo dear to us; they will follow a little after: When we die we are <hi>gather'd to our people,</hi> and go unto our Fathers; and we ſhall there have the acquaintance of more and far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Friends; Angels, and Archangels, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out number:
<note place="margin">Dan. 7.10.</note> 
                  <hi>for thouſand thouſands miniſter unto God, and ten thouſand times ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſtand before him:</hi> what an unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble joy will it be to have a familiar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation with the Patriarchs, Prophets,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:63173:36"/>Apoſtles, Martyrs, and all the faithful Servants of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>And as the pleaſures of this life, are as nothing, if they be weighed in an even ballance, with the glories of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, to which we paſs by the gate of death: ſo alſo death it ſelf is not to be feared by us; for though it is called the moſt terrible of all evils, becauſe it ſeparates thoſe two intimate Friends, Soul and Body; and delivers up the Body which was here ſo tenderly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved and provided for, to be eaten up by Worms: though death conſider'd in it ſelf be the puniſhment of ſin, and befalls us by the Divine Maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and though death be to be dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by one who is involved in a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity of worldly buſineſs, and is not provided for his departure out of this life, and ſo is very doubtful of his future ſtate: yet foraſmuch as by the death of Chriſt, it is made the way and paſſage to eternal life; to a good man, who is prepared for an happy death, it is not at all to be fear'd: <hi>that the day of death is better than the day of ones birth:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> For when we are born, we enter into this World, which is a ſcene full of miſeries and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:63173:37"/>but when we die, we leave them all, and are tranſlated into that other bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed life, which is repleniſh'd with all kinds of felicities.</p>
               <p>We are firſt of all in this World ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to the ſlavery of our corruptions and original Sin, whilſt afterwards the ſeeds of many luſts ſpring up in us, infidelity, ambition, covetouſneſs, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, envy, uncleanneſs, and ſuch like: thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> complains, that <hi>he was ſold under ſin:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7.14.</note> This is the height of miſery, and to a man enflamed with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire after an holy life, and in whoſe breaſt one ſpark of piety remains, nothing can happen more grievous, than the corruptions of the fleſh: of this the Apoſtle farther complains;
<note place="margin">Ibid. v. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>I know, that in me (that is in my fleſh) dwelleth no good thing; for to will is preſent with me, but how to perform that which is good. I find not: For the good that I would, I do not, but the evil which I would not,
<note place="margin">v. 24.</note> that I do,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from the body of this death?</hi> None can be wholly freed from this corruption of the fleſh, in this life, but after death, we ſhall be altogether deliver'd from it, and they who ſhall be thought worthy to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:63173:37"/>into the bleſſed life above, ſhall ſin no more.</p>
               <p>And farther a great trouble and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it is to pious Men, that they are forc'd to live and ſojourn amongſt ſo many wicked Perſons,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 120.5.</note> like Sheep amongſt Wolves; this made <hi>David</hi> cry out, <hi>Wo is me, that I am conſtrained to dwell with</hi> Meſech, <hi>and to have my Habitation among the Tents of</hi> Kedar: Beſides our Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is expoſed to the greateſt dangers, <hi>the Devil as a Roaring Lyon,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8.</note> walketh about ſeeking whom he may devour.</hi> The World is daily exciting us to Sin by evil Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and fair Promiſes; the Snares where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Satan and the World endeavours to intrap us, are every where laid for us; in Riches, in Meat and Drink, in our Eyes and in our Ears, in our Words and in our Actions; now Death wholly frees us from the Temptations of the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil: And not only from theſe, but alſo from all the Calamities and Misfortues which ſo uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happen to Mankind in this Mortal Life: That this Life is full of troubles, there needs not many words to prove; ſince both Sacred and Prophane Authors com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the Miſeries of Humane Life,
<note place="margin">Job 14.1.</note> whilſt they teach that <hi>Man that is born of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:63173:38"/>a Woman, is of few days, and full of Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> And that <hi>the very name of Man, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports all miſeries:</hi> This truth we all daily experience: For how lamentable is our Nativity? To how many evils is our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy expoſed? Our youth, to how many injuries and dangers is it obnoxious? With how many cares is our Manhood diſtracted? And how is our old Age Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with Calamities? What reaſon then we have to fear death, which at once frees us from all theſe miſeries, which is the only ſafe Haven to us, who ſail on this Stormy and Tempeſtuous Sea?</p>
               <p>Nor doth death only deliver us from Sin, and all the Troubles of this World, but is alſo the gate through which we are to paſs into Eternal Life; wherein the juſt ſhall enjoy the moſt delightful Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God the Father, of Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, of the Holy Ghoſt the Comforter, and of all the Angels and Bleſſed Spirits: How great this future Happineſs and Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude is, the mind of Man cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, nor words expreſs? And although our Bodies ſhall rot in the grave, or be other ways diſſolved, yet is there no danger that we ſhall be ſeparated from Chriſt, to whom we are joyned by the Bond of the Spirit, but the dead ſhall
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:63173:38"/>remain united to Chriſt, both in their Bodies and in their Souls, and in the laſt Judgment, their Souls and Bodies being made one, ſhall ariſe together to Eternal Glory: Hence in Holy Writ, Death is called, a Sleep; and the Grave, a Bed or Dormitory:</p>
               <p>For all theſe reaſons the True Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is ſo provided, that not only death, but ſudden death alſo doth not affright him; men indeed do uſually, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, dread ſudden death; but if we duly conſider it, a wicked life ſpent without Repentance, is much more to be fear'd, than a ſudden death; nor is a ſudden death bad, becauſe it is ſudden, but becauſe for the moſt part it overtakes Men unprepar'd, and impenitent, and ſo caſts them headlong into Deſtruction; whereas if it finds us ready, a ſudden death is not evil, but rather a more ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy paſſage from this, to an Happy and Eternal Life.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:63173:39"/>
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MOſt Merciful Father, open and enlighten the Eyes of my Mind, to ſee and rightly conſider the Miſery and Vanity of this preſent life, that I may not ſet my affections on the World, nor the things in it; but may with my whole Heart, long after the Joys of Heaven: O Lord excite in me an ardent Deſire after the Celeſtial Life, and vouchſafe me ſome fore taſte of it, by the ſweetneſs whereof, the bitterneſs of death may be ſo allay'd, that I may be daily ready to leave this World, and deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt our Lord,</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:63173:39"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>The Duty of a Chriſtian.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE third Head of the Preparation for a Bleſſed Death,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Non poteſt malè mori, qui bene vixerit.</hi> de diſcipline chriſtiana, cap. 12.</note> was to live holily, and to enter into ſuch a courſe of life, as becomes a Chriſtian; for as St. <hi>Augustin</hi> ſays, <hi>No Body can die ill, that hath liv'd well:</hi> Now he lives well that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms the Duties of a Chriſtian: He therefore who is mindful of his Eternal Salvation, muſt diligently conſider what the Duty of a Chriſtian is, or what way of living may beſt conduce towards the attaintment of everlaſting life after this: For he who would die like a Chriſtian, muſt live as a Chriſtian: But he who lives wickedly, ſhall die wickedly; and ſhall ariſe and be condemned with the Wicked: Now although there be many Duties which belong to Chriſtians in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with other Men, yet are they not peculiar to a Chriſtian, but are ordained for the preſervation of Humane Society, and honeſt Behaviour in the World:
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:63173:40"/>One kind of Duty there is, which proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belongs to a Chriſtian, which only is needful, and which whoever performs, it will be well with him hereafter for evermore: And what that duty is, the very name of a Chriſtian doth ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intimate: For whereas the Sects of all Philoſophers and Religions have received their Names from their Author and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; whoſe Precepts, Ordinances, and Inſtitutions they follow; in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Chriſtians are ſo called, becauſe they only imitate Chriſt, and as much as in them lies, tread in his ſteps, and obey his command, and moreover (what cannot be ſaid of any other Religion) a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is one, who doth not live himſelf, but Chriſt liveth in him by Faith,
<note place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> ſo that Chriſt is the life of Chriſtians, who thenceforth manifeſts himſelf in all their actions.</p>
               <p>It is then chiefly requiſite, a Chriſtian ſhould know who Chriſt is, whoſe Name he bears, and to whom he gave up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the Sacrament of Baptiſm; what he hath done for our Salvation, and what he requires of us to do:</p>
               <p>To this end, firſt we are to remember, that Man was Created by God after his own Image;
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> that is, as the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:63173:40"/>it,
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.24.</note> 
                  <hi>in true Holineſs and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> ſo that his underſtanding was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to God, and gave to him alone all Honour and Glory: Him alone he lov'd, reverenced and worſhipped, and with Him hereafter he ſhould have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd an immortal, eternal, and moſt bleſſed life:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> 'Tis to be remark'd, that our firſt Parents fell from that primitive Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Righteouſneſs, and ſo loſt the Image of God; for after that by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of the Devil, they had enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a love of themſelves contrary to God, and to the love of their Creator, preferring their own Glory and Delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, before the love and glory of God, and deſiring to be equal with God himſelf; their underſtandings were preſently over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread with ignorance and blindneſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Wiſdom: Their Wills grew Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory and Diſobedient to God, and all their affections were perverſe, irregular, and out of order, ſo that now the thoughts of man from his infancy are evil; and thus man not only fell from that eternal life, for which he was Created, but alſo became obnoxious to eternal Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> 'Tis firmly to be believ'd, that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:63173:41"/>God took pitty on fallen Mankind, and ſent his Son to take upon him Humane Fleſh, and being made Man, did by ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering and dying ſatisfie for us, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us from eternal death: And did by his Merits, relied on by a true Faith, again make us Heirs of that bleſſed life, which by our ſins we loſt; and reſtored in us the decayed image of God, and made us his, and Sanctified us by his Holy Spirit, that we might ſerve him in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs all the days of our life.</p>
               <p>From whence it plainly appears, who Chriſt is, and what is the duty of a Chriſtian; <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt is our Redeemer, who reconciled us unto his Father, and by his Merits made us his Brethren and Coheirs of his Kingdom, when we were enemies to God, defiled with ſin, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be puniſhed with eternal death: And a Chriſtian (who derives his name from Chriſt) is one who acknowledges that he was indeed created by God in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs, but by the Wiles of Satan fell from, and rebelled againſt God, and ſo being polluted by the ſtains of Original Sin, and contami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated with many actual Tranſgreſſions, he became liable to the wrath of God,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:63173:41"/>and everlaſting puniſhment; from which he is freed and redeemed by the alone Merits and Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which by Faith is imputed unto him; ſo that now he is to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take ſuch a way of living, as may be well pleaſing not to the Devil, but unto God, and therefore he is to avoid all ſins, from which he is redeemed by the pretious Merits of Chriſt, and to ſerve God alone in an holy and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous life:</p>
               <p>And from hence ariſes a threefold duty of a Chriſtian: The firſt is to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge himſelf a ſinner, and to bewail his ſins: Secondly, To believe Chriſt to be his Redeemer, and to truſt only in his Merits. Thirdly, To obey his Laws, to follow the guidance of the Holy Spirit, not to relapſe into ſins, from which by the death of Chriſt he is redeemed, but to love God above all things, and his Neighbour as himſelf: Or to comprize all in a word; the life of a Chriſtian is a continual Repentance. For ſince he is defiled with Original Sin, and even the <hi>Juſt Man falls ſeven times:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 24.16.</note> He will therefore be always ſorrowful for his ſins, and ſly to the Merits of Chriſt; and ſerve God in true Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:63173:42"/>and Holineſs: In ſum, 'tis the Duty of a Chriſtian to believe in Chriſt, and to live holily; which if he doth, for Chriſts ſake he will be acceptable unto God, and ſhall in the end, inherit eternal life: But if he ſhall be deprived of this happineſs, if he is not in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with God, although he ſhould poſſeſs the Riches of the whole World, although he were Monarch over all the Earth, although he were wiſer than the beſt Philoſophers, yet would all be in vain, and to no purpoſe: <hi>Vanity of Vanities,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.</note> all is Vanity,</hi> except to ſerve God, and to pleaſe him: There are indeed many things to be done, which are allowed of God; but there is one thing neceſſary: None ſhall be Condemned in the laſt Day, that they were not rich, that they were not in high places, that they did not enjoy great honours, that they were ignorant of many nice Subtilties of Nature: But they alone ſhall be Condemned, who do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt, and who are not the Children of God.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:63173:42"/>
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GRant, O Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that I may never forget thoſe Vows wherewith I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged my ſelf unto thee, in the Holy Sacrament of Baptiſm, but that renouncing the Devil and all his Works, I may obey thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with my whole Heart; and confeſſing my ſelf to be a Miſerable Sinner, I may confide in thy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and ſerve Thee in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, all the days of my life.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:63173:43"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>That we muſt repent: And firſt of ſorrowing for our ſins.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOR as much as the Chriſtian knows, that he is conceiv'd and born in ſins, and that in this corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Humane Nature, no body can ſufficiently reſiſt the Temptations of the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil; that <hi>there is no Man which ſinneth not;
<note place="margin">2 Chr. 6.36. Prov. 20.9.</note> for who can ſay, I have made my Heart clean, I am pure from my ſin?</hi> and that even <hi>the Juſt man falleth ſeven times;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 24.16.</note> therefore he hates and bewails his ſins, and confeſſeth that by them, he hath provoked Gods anger againſt him, ſo that he juſtly deſerveth the eternal pains of Hell: But the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an muſt bewail his ſins ſeriouſly, and from his heart:
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.10.</note> 
                  <hi>For that is godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row which worketh Repentance unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, not to be repented of,</hi> (that is a true ſorrow for ſins joyn'd with faith:) Now this grief and ſadneſs, the Holy Ghoſt excites in us, as alſo doth the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:63173:43"/>Conſideration and Meditation of Chriſts Paſſion: As if a Man conſiders, who he is, whom he hath offended, who it is that is angry with him, and that his ſins were the cauſe of his Saviours Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: For Man from himſelf is nothing, but he is Gods Creature, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever any one hath, he hath it from God: But God is the Creator of all things, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, Omnipotent, Immenſe, moſt Wiſe, moſt Good, and moſt Great; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that between Man and God, there is no proportion: And yet Man by his ſins rebell'd againſt God, and deliver'd himſelf up into the Bondage of Satan, and ſo provoked the infinite anger of his God againſt him: Now the Paſſion of Chriſt is the Mirrior of the Divine anger: And whoever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders with himſelf the reaſons that mov'd the Son of God to become Man, to ſuffer and to die, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth that it was the ſins of the World, which could no other ways be atton'd for, than by the Death and Paſſion of the Son of God himſelf; he who ſhall conſider that Man, who is Duſt and Aſhes, fell away from his Creator, the great and good God, and liſted himſelf
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:63173:44"/>under the Devils Banner, and ſo by his ſins, provoked Gods anger enough to have thrown him headlong into Hell; and withal ſhall confeſs it to be in part his own fault, that the Son of God underwent ſuch Grief and Torments for others Crimes; no doubt but ſuch an one will abhor himſelf, and be amazed at the conſideration of his own guilt; and if he were left to himſelf to rely upon his own ſtrength, and knew no ways of appeaſing the wrath of God, he muſt of neceſſity be driven to deſpair.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WO is me O Lord, who was conceived and born in ſin! the thoughts of my heart are inclined unto evil from my Youth! Wo is me who have ſinned againſt thee my Creatour, and bountiful Lord, and have done evil in thy ſight: But I acknowledge mine iniquity, and my ſins are ever before me:
<note place="margin">Jet. 9.1.</note> Oh that my
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:63173:44"/>head were waters and mine eyes a fountain of tears, that I might weep day and night for my ſins, whereby I have ſo often offended thee my Lord and Creatour, whether ſhall I fly? who will intercede for me? who will deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me in the day of thy fierce anger, that I periſh not for ever: Alas! there is none to ſave but thy Son our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: But foraſmuch as faith in him is not our own work, but thy gift, bleſſed Lord, let thy Holy Spirit excite, preſerve and daily increaſe in my heart a true and lively faith:
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.27.</note> O Holy Father ſince no man knoweth the Son but thou only; neither knoweth any man thee, ſave thy Son, and he to whomſoever the Son will reveal thee; draw me I beſeech thee unto him, that he may lead me unto thee, leaſt I die in my ſins: Vouchſafe to ſtrengthen my weak Faith, and perfect that good Work which thou haſt begun in me:
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:63173:45"/>Eſtabliſh in me a firm Faith in my Saviour to the laſt breath of my life, that amongſt the many vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous errors and opinions of this World, I may not in the leaſt be perverted from the true faith, but may always ask and obtain the remiſſion of my ſins from thee, through the merits and interceſſion of the ſame thy Son our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:63173:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>That we are to fly for refuge to the mercies of God, and to believe in Chriſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUT the Chriſtian is not to deſpair, altho' he muſt acknowledge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be a ſinner;
<note place="margin">John 3.16.</note> but for as much as he knows that <hi>God ſo loved the World, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life;</hi> he therefore puts his whole truſt and confidence in the mercies of God through the merits of Chriſt: For the merciful God hath promiſed pardon of ſins to true Penitents; this we find in divers places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.
<note place="margin">Ezek. 33.12.</note> 
                  <hi>As for the wickedneſs of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he ſhall not fall thereby, in the day that he turneth from his wickedneſs;
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.9.</note> for God is long-ſuffering to us ward, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:63173:46"/>all ſhould come to repentance: As I live ſaith the Lord God,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 33.11.</note> I have no pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turn from his way and live: A broken and a contrite heart,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.17.</note> God will not deſpiſe: Therefore alſo now ſaith the Lord, turn ye even to me with all your heart, and with faſting, and with weeping,
<note place="margin">Joel 2.13.</note> and with mourning: And rent your heart, and not your garments, and turn unto the Lord your God: for he is gracious and merciful, ſlow to anger and of great kindneſs, and repenteth him of the evil:
<note place="margin">Zechar. 1.3.</note> Turn ye unto me ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, and I will turn unto you:
<note place="margin">Pſ. 69.33. Mat. 12.20.</note> Seek ye after God, and your Soul ſhall live: A bruiſed reed ſhall he not break, and ſmoaking flax ſhall he not quench:
<note place="margin">Act. 3.19.</note> Repent ye therefore, and be converted, that your ſins may be blotted out:</hi> And therefore the true Penitent may with affiance approach unto God, and ſay;
<note place="margin">Pſ. 130.3.</note> 
                  <hi>If thou Lord ſhouldeſt mark ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities; O Lord, who ſhall ſtand: Father I have ſinned againſt Heaven,
<note place="margin">Luk. 15.21.</note> and before thee, and am no more worthy to be called thy Son:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 51.1.</note> But, <hi>have mercy upon me according to thy loving kindneſs; according unto the multitudes of thy tender mercies:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lu. 18.13.</note> And, <hi>God be merciful
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:63173:46"/>unto me a ſinner.</hi> Nor let him in the leaſt doubt of the mercy of God, whilſt he relies on the merits of Chriſt;
<note place="margin">Mat. 18.11. 1 Joh. 1.7.</note> 
                  <hi>For the Son of Man came to ſave that which was loſt; and the blood of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſin.
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.2.</note> And he is the propitiation for our ſins, and not for ours only, but alſo for the ſins of the whole World:
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.1.</note> There is therefore now no condemnation to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> ſo that he may reſt quiet in the mercies of God, and in the merits of Chriſt, as knowing that a full ranſom was paid for his ſins, and that a moſt abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perfect righteouſneſs, able to ſtand before the judgment of God, was purchaſed and obtained for ſinners by the moſt holy Obedience of Chriſt, which he performed to his Father, both in his life and death; and which the Holy Spirit offers to all the World in the Word and Sacraments, deſiring them to accept of it: And to thoſe who do not reſiſt theſe means, he excites, increaſes, and confirms their Faith, that they may receive the grace of God purchaſed by Chriſt's merits, and tender'd unto them in the Divine Word and holy Sacraments:
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:63173:47"/>ſo that they may be confident, that he who hath begun a good work in them, will alſo perfect it, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them in grace unto the end of their lives: For, ſaith St. <hi>Paul, I am perſwaded that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, Nor height,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8. ult.</note> nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEhold, O Lord, I was ſhapen in iniquity, and in ſin did my Mother conceive me: I know that in my fleſh dwelleth no good thing; and I ſee another law in my members waring againſt the law of my mind: from this corruption of nature it proceeds that I am ſo diſobedient to to thy Laws and Commandments;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:63173:47"/>even from my infancy until now, I have infinite ways tranſgreſſed them in thought, word, and deed; the good things which I ought, I have not done, and the evil things which I ought not I have committed; ſo great is the number of my ſins, that I can no longer remember them all. O Heavenly Father, I am not worthy to be called thy Son; but I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my tranſgreſſion, and my ſin is ever before me: Have mercy upon me therefore, O God, according to thy great goodneſs, and cleanſe me from all, even my moſt ſecret ſins; enter not into judgment with thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and remember not the ſins of my youth: Lord, deſpiſe not a broken and a contrite heart, for with thee there is mercy and plenteous redemption: To thee then, O thou Son of God, and my Saviour, I fly for ſuccour: Thou cameſt into the World to ſave ſinners; thou haſt
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:63173:48"/>called unto thee all that are weary and heavy laden, and haſt promiſed to give them reſt and eaſe: Behold I come unto thee, bowed together with the weight of my ſins, O do thou lift me up; for thou art the Lamb of God that takeſt away the ſins of the World; thou dideſt that all that believe in thee ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life: Lord Jeſu I believe in thee, O pity and help my infirmities,</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:63173:48"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>That we muſt live Holily.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUT it is not enough barely to know, that Chriſt died for ſin: Since the Devils are not ignorant of this: mere <hi>knowledge which puffeth up,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.1.</note> is one thing, and a vain boaſting of Faith is another, and a true lively Faith is another; which as by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward formal Act, it receives and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends Chriſt with all his benefits to Juſtification,
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> ſo alſo outwardly <hi>it work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by love:</hi> And therefore Chriſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving redeemed us from the hands of our Enemies, we ought to ſerve him in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs all the days of our life: To this purpoſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts us:
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.15.</note> 
                  <hi>That Christ died for all, that they which live, ſhould not henceforth live unto themſelves, but unto him which died for them, and roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain;
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:63173:49"/>For the grace of God that bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Salvation,
<note place="margin">Tit. 2.11.</note> hath appeared to all Men: Teaching us that denying ungodlineſs and worldly Luſts,
<note place="margin">verſ. 12.</note> we ſhould live Soberly, Righteouſly, and Godly in this preſent World:
<note place="margin">verſ. 13.</note> Looking for that bleſſed hope, and the glorious appearing of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt: Who gave himſelf for us,
<note place="margin">verſ. 14.</note> that he might Redeem us from all iniquity, and purifie unto himſelf a peculiar People, zealous of good works:</hi> All they therefore that think to have their ſins remitted, whilſt they go on in their wickedneſs, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves, and make a mock at the Merits of Chriſt, and may ſo fall away,
<note place="margin">Heb. 6.6.</note> as even <hi>to Crucifie unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Son of God afreſh,
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> and put him to an open ſhame: And account the blood of the Covenant wherewith they were Sanctified, an unholy thing, and do deſpight unto the ſpirit of grace:</hi> For ſince Chriſt hath redeemed us from the Slavery of Satan, and reſtored us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to our former liberty; it is very fitting that we ſhould lead a new life, bid farewel to all iniquity, and ſerve God with a <hi>pure heart fervently.</hi> Now this reſtoring Man to his priſtine ſtate, in which God at firſt created him, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:63173:49"/>from whence by ſin he fell, is in holy Writ called a <hi>Renovation:</hi> Or a <hi>new Creature:</hi> For ſo ſays the Apoſtle:
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.22, 23, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Put off concerning the former Converſation, the old Man, which is corrupt according to the deceitful Lusts: And be renewed in the Spirit of your mind; and put on the new Man, which after God is Created in Righteouſneſs, in true Holineſs: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore putting away lying, ſpeak every Man truth with his Neighbour, for we are members one of another: Be ye angry and ſin not, let not the Sun go down upon your wrath: Neither give place to the Devil: Let him that stole, steal no more; but rather let him labour, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with his hands, the thing which is good, that he may have to give to him that needeth: Let no corrupt Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion proceed out of your mouth, but that which is good to the uſe of edifying, that it may minister grace unto the Hearers: And grieve not the Holy Spirit of God, whereby ye are ſealed unto the day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. Let all bitterneſs, and wrath, and anger, and clamour, and evil ſpeaking be put away from you with all Malice. And be ye kind one to another, tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, forgiving one another, even as
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:63173:50"/>God for Chriſts ſake hath forgiven you:</hi> And a little after:
<note place="margin">Eph. 5.3.</note> 
                  <hi>But Fornication and all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, or Covetouſneſs, let it not be once named amongſt you:</hi> Although it plainly appears from this Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Apoſtle, what a Regenerate Man (whoſe ſins are pardon'd) is to do, and what he is to avoid; yet we may briefly comprize the whole exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Godlineſs under theſe two Heads, <hi>viz.</hi> the love of God, and of our Neighbour: This is the Sum of all the Commandments; as our Saviour himſelf teaches us,
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.37. Luke 10.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God, with all thy Heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy Strength, and with all thy Mind; and thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as thy ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:63173:50"/>
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>O <hi>Merciful Father, who in thy Son Jeſus Chriſt, haſt pardoned all my ſins; what ſhall I render unto thee for all the Benefits which thou haſt beſtowed on me? Grant that I may delight my ſelf in thy Commandments; that I may not love the World, nor the things in it, but may Crucifie my fleſh, with its Affections and Luſts; guide me with thy Holy Spirit, that I may daily perſevere in true Repentance, may war a good warfare, keep Faith and a good Conſcience, and increaſe more and more in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs, working that which is well pleaſing in thy ſight: And for as much as of my ſelf, I am not able to do any good thing, do thou, O Lord, who giveſt both to will and to do, perfect that good work which
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:63173:51"/>thou haſt begun in me, and bring it to an Happy Iſſue, and keep me in all my ways, that I depart not from thy Statutes; Lead me in the paths of thy Commandments: Thy word is a Lanthern unto my Feet, and a light unto my paths: Order my ſteps in thy word, and let not any iniquity have Dominion over me,</hi> Pſ. 119.133.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:63173:51"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>That God is to be loved above all things.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOR as much as God at firſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us; Chriſt by his Death re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed us from eternal Death; and the Holy Spirit ſanctifies us, and leads us to everlaſting life, therefore are we to love God above all things whatever: Love naturally deſires what is good and excellent, and what any one loves that he always eſteems beſt, moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and beautiful; now there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be ſuppos'd better and more beautiful than God, and therefore he is to be loved above all things: This is the firſt Commandment;
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods before me:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 5.7.6.4. Mar. 12.29.</note> And <hi>hear O Iſrael, the Lord our God is one Lord: And thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God, with all thine Heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy Might:</hi> He
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:63173:52"/>who loves God above all things, hath no other Gods; but who ever loves any thing more than God, he makes that his God; for he prefers it before God, and ſets it up as an Idol in his Heart: Therefore a Chriſtian is to deſpiſe all things in reſpect of God, how great and profitable, how beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and deſirable ſoever they may appear, and whatever he loves, he therefore loves them, becauſe they are dear and acceptable unto God; but whatever God hates, that the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is to deſpiſe: Thus our Saviour teacheth us:
<note place="margin">Luk. 14.26, 27.</note> 
                  <hi>If any Man come to me, and hate not his Father and Mother, and Wiſe, and Children, and Brethren and Sisters, yea, and his own Life alſo, he cannot be my Diſciple.
<note place="margin">Joh. 12.25.</note> He that loveth his Life, ſhall loſe it, and he that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his Life in this World, ſhall keep it unto Life Eternal.</hi> That is to ſay, a Chriſtian ought to deſpiſe himſelf, and all that he hath, and every thing in the World in reſpect of God; to deſire nothing, to love nothing that may alienate his affections from God, however ſpecious it may ſeem, or how much ſo ever it may tend to the grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:63173:52"/>of his pleaſure, profit, fame or glory: So that though he ſtudies the practice of Vertue, yet he doth it not to advance his own vain Glory and Honour, but becauſe no knoweth 'tis acceptable to God; and ſo whatſoever he doth, he doth all to the glory of God: This is truly to die to the World, when we can deſpiſe Pleaſures, Riches, Honours, and all the World enjoys; when God is dearer to us, than any thing beſides, and when we dare not do any evil for the love of any Man or thing in the whole World: If this ſeem hard, yet is it very juſt and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable: For if we love any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we find it profitable to us, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that every thing we poſſeſs, we have from God; if we love any other things becauſe they are good; God is the chiefeſt good, yea, goodneſs it ſelf: If we love Riches, all things are Gods, he is Lord of Heaven and Earth, he filleth the needy with good things, and diſpenſeth Riches to whom he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth: If we love Honour, what great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Honour can there be, than when the Son of Man ſhall come in great power and glory, that they who have
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:63173:53"/>loved him, and for his ſake have left all things in the World, ſhould alſo ſit upon ſeats, and Judge the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> All Worldly things are changeable and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary, and the various viciſſitudes of Humane Affairs, occaſion nothing but Cares, Sorrows and Vexations of Soul: But the love of God cauſeth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Peace and Tranquility of Mind; according to that of <hi>David:
<note place="margin">Pſ. 73.36.</note> My Fleſh and my Heart faileth: But God is the ſtrength of my Heart, and my portion for ever.</hi> If for the ſake of God we loſe our Worldly goods, the great God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is more worth than all, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever enjoys him, hath all things elſe: For in God are all things that we can wiſh for or deſire; as ſaith our Lord: <hi>Every one that hath forſaken Houſes or Brethren,
<note place="margin">Mat. 19.29.</note> or Siſters, or Father, or Mother, or Wife, or Children, or Lands for my names ſake, ſhall receive an hundred fold, and ſhall inherit everlasting life:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 14.23.</note> And again: <hi>if a Man love me, my Father will love him, and we will come unto him, and make our abode with him.</hi> This may ſeem hard to Fleſh and Blood, but Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nity cannot otherwiſe ſubſiſt: The true Chriſtian loves nothing better than
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:63173:53"/>God, and whoever doth, prefers the Creature before the Creator.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, the Chriſtian doth all to the glory of God; he ſeeks not his own pleaſure or profit, or honour in any thing, but doth all out of love to God, and for Gods honour: And he that loves God truly and ſincerely, loves only thoſe things that are dear and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God; and hates all things that God hates: This Holy Men in all Ages ſtudiouſly perform'd, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Martyrs; the World indeed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed them as fools, but they were the moſt prudent Men living: For is not he the wiſeſt Man, that deſpiſeth vile and trifling things, and ſets a juſt value upon things that are beſt, and moſt uſeful? For as our Saviour ſays,
<note place="margin">Mat. 16.26.</note> 
                  <hi>what ſhall it profit a Man, to gain the whole World, and loſe his own Soul?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Virtue it ſelf, and good works are not pleaſing to God, if in them a Man ſeeks his own glory, and not the glory of God alone: And from hence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, how vain the thoughts of Men are; they ſpend many Days and Nights in Labour and Study, that they may get Learning, and appear renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:63173:54"/>in the World; but to be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Divine Nature, to acquire a Bleſſed and Eternal Life, they can ſcarcely ſpare ſo much time from their buſineſs, as to recite one ſerious Prayer: What troubles do Merchants undergo, how many dangers do they run in hopes of being rich? And of how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle value are the things they gain? Nay, were they as truly great and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious as they ſeem to be, yet Death would quickly deprive them of all: But on the contrary, how great are thoſe good things, which God will give in the other life to thoſe that love him? Of which we have already treated in the fourth Chapter. That life will be void of all evil, and repleniſh'd with all the good and happineſs that can be deſired, there we ſhall openly behold the Glory and Majeſty of God, and enjoy Communion with him; there we ſhall not only hear the Hymns and Songs that are ſung without intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in praiſe of the Eternal King, by the Angels, Archangels, and all the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but ſhall alſo aſſiſt in their Quire, and praiſe God for ever and ever: Oh! How Bleſſed, how beautiful is the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:63173:54"/>Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem!</hi> Very glorious things are ſpoken of thee, thou City of God: In thee there is no darkneſs, no night, no cold nor heat, no al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of Seaſons, no hunger nor thirſt, no labour nor wearineſs, no ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs nor death; the glory of God ſhall enlighten thee; and the pure immaculate Lamb ſhall be thy Light.
<note place="margin">Rev. 21.23.</note> There God ſhall give us meat, of which whoſoever eateth, he ſhall hunger no more; and drink, of which whoſoever drinketh, he ſhall thirſt no more: God ſhall be our ſtrength, our health and our life: God will there be all in all.</p>
               <p>And now who in his right mind would not deſpiſe and loath theſe vain Worldly things, and love God alone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things elſe, that ſo after Death, when all things here below vaniſh and diſappear, he may be made a partaker of this Bleſſedneſs, wherein God will be all in all?</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:63173:55"/>
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O Merciful Lord, inlighten the Eyes of my mind, that I may conſider what immenſe benefits I have received from thee: When I was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, thou didſt create me after thine own Image; when by my ſins, I was juſtly doom'd to the pains of Hell, thou didſt redeem me there from by the Death of thy Son, and haſt ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me with thy Holy Spirit: Lord, by how many Bonds am I obliged to love thee, my only good! How vain and empty are theſe Tranſitory things, which after this life is ended, muſt all be left behind: Grant therefore that I may ſet my affections on things above, that I may deſire thee alone, and be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flam'd with the love of thee, that after Death, I may be tranſlated to the joys
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:63173:55"/>and bleſſedneſs of thy glorious Kingdom, and live with thee for ever and ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>That we are to love our Neighbour.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter God, our Neighbour is to be beloved, whom a Chriſtian ought to love as himſelf: And theſe two, the love of God, and of our Neigheour, are joyned together by an indiſſoluble Bond, ſo that the love of God can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſeparated from the love of our Neighbour: If any one ſhall ſay, <hi>I love God, and hate his Brother, he is a Lyar.</hi> He who is <hi>angry with his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without cauſe,</hi> doth not love God; no one can hurt his Brother, but at the ſame time he offends God: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore amongſt the Characters of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, this is one of the chief, to love our Neighbour: <hi>A new Commandment,</hi>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:63173:56"/>ſaith our Saviour,
<note place="margin">John 13.34, 35</note> 
                  <hi>I give unto you, that ye love one another: By this ſhall all Men know that ye are my Diſciples, if ye have love one to another.</hi> Although a Chriſtian be endued with all other Vertues, yet without Charity, they will all profit him nothing? Of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> thus ſpeaks:
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.1, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Though I ſpeak with the Tongues of Men and of Angels, and have not Charity, I am become as ſounding Braſs, or a tinkling Cymbal. And though I have the gift of Prophecy, and understand all Mysteries, and all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and have no Charity, I am no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> &amp;c. In the laſt Judgment, the Faith of Men ſhall be judged by their Charity: Whilſt the Juſt Judge ſhall ſay to the Bleſſed:
<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>I was an hungred, and ye gave me meat, I was thirſty, and ye gave me drink, I was a stranger, and ye took me in, naked and ye cloathed me, I was ſick, and ye viſited me; I was in priſon, and ye came unto me; for as much as ye have done it unto the leaſt of theſe, ye have done it unto me.</hi> And on the contrary, to the wicked he ſhall ſay: <hi>I was an hungred, and ye gave me no meat, I was thirſty, and ye gave me no drink, I was a ſtranger, and ye took me
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:63173:56"/>not in, naked, and ye cloathed me not, ſick and in priſon, and ye viſited me not;</hi> and <hi>foraſmuch as ye did it not to one of the leaſt of theſe, ye did it not to me:</hi> By this Chriſtians are diſtinguiſhed from the Heathen; they indeed love their Friends; but Chriſtians muſt love their Enemies, as our Saviour teacheth us: <hi>But I ſay unto you: love your Enemies,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.44, &amp;c.</note> Bleſs them that Curſe you, do good to them that hate you, pray for them which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitefully uſe you, and perſecute you: That ye may be the Children of your Father which is in Heaven, for he maketh the Sun to riſe on the evil and on the good and and ſendeth rain on the Juſt, and on the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt: For if ye love them which love you, what reward have ye? Do not even the</hi> Publicans <hi>the ſame? And if ye ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute your Brethren only, what do ye more than others, do not even the</hi> Publicans <hi>ſo? Be ye therefore perfect, even as your Father which is in Heaven is perfect:</hi> For in this the Eminency and Prerogative of a Chriſtian conſiſts, in overcoming the World and the Fleſh: Accordingly St. <hi>Paul</hi> thus adviſeth us;
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.17, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Recompence to no Man Evil for Evil: Provide things honeſt in the ſight of all Men: If it be
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:63173:57"/>poſſible as much as lieth in you,
<note place="margin">verſ. 19.</note> live peaceably with all Men: Dearly beloved, avenge not your ſelves — If thine Enemy hunger,
<note place="margin">verſ. 20.</note> feed him, if he thirſt, give him drink; for in ſo doing, thou ſhalt heap Coals of fire on his Head. Be not overcome of Evil, but overcome Evil with good.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſ. 21.</note>
               </p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LORD Jeſus, who haſt given us a new Commandment, that we ſhould love one another; and wenteſt before us by thy Example in doing good, and praying for thine Enemies, grant that we may bear a brotherly love and kindneſs to all Men, that we may hurt no body, but do good to all Men, even to our Enemies, and commit all Revenge to thee alone: Take from us, O Lord, Anger, Hatred, Malice, and all bitterneſs of Spirit, that the Sun may not go down upon our wrath, but that we may forgive thoſe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:63173:57"/>that have Treſpaſſed againſt us, even as we deſire thee to forgive us our Treſpaſſes; grant unto us kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and good will, that our Faith may work by love, and all Men may ſay, that we are thy Diſciples indeed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>That we muſt guard our minds from Capital Sins.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALthough a Chriſtian, if he loveth God above all; and his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as himſelf, and orders all his Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the love of God, and of his Neighbour, will not eaſily be tempted to commit any Heinous Crime; yet becauſe ſins do eaſily inſinuate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the mask of good; and the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil do endeavour a thouſand ways by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements, by deceits, or by force, to tempt us from our good purpoſes and reſolutions of living well; it therefore behoves a Chriſtian to arm himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Aſſaults of all Capital Sins: For as in War, he that knows the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:63173:58"/>is near, provideth himſelf with all neceſſary Weapons, keeps Watches and Sentinels, that ſo he may at all times be in a readineſs to oppoſe the Enemy: In like manner it is our Duty, to have always our Spiritual Armour at hand, with which we may reſiſt the Enemies of our Salvation, the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil: This is that Warfare by which we overcome the World, and our own ſelves, and we ought daily to improve our ſelves in it: Wherefore if Men would but take half the pains in vanquiſhing their Luſts, and implant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Piety in their Minds, as they do in getting Riches, hunting after Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and reſolving nice and intricate Queſtions, there would be fewer of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences in the World, and the exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Vertue would be much more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and vigorous amongſt Men.</p>
               <p>And whereas <hi>all that are in the World, are the Luſts of the Fleſh, the Lust of the Eyes, and the Pride of Life;</hi> or the love of Pleaſures, Riches, and Honours;
<note place="margin">1 John 2.16.</note> and thoſe Enormous Sins which ariſe from hence, as Pride, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, Luxury, Envy, Anger, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and Hatred, and the like: It is therefore the Duty of a Chriſtian dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:63173:58"/>to conſider, how he may beſt fortifie himſelf againſt theſe vices:</p>
               <p>And firſt againſt <hi>Pride:</hi> The Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an may eaſily cure himſelf of this Evil, by accuſtoming himſelf to Humility, and conſidering how little one Man is better than another: We are born all alike, one wants Meat and Drink as well as another; and <hi>all the labour of Man is for his Mouth, and yet the Appetite is not filled;</hi> one is ſick as well as another, and we all die, and return unto the Earth from whence we were taken: And indeed this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration alone, that in a ſhort time we muſt all die, is ſufficient to keep us from Pride, and lifting up our ſelves above our fellows; for ſhould any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be high minded, and boaſt themſelves of their Noble Extract, their Beauty, Wiſdom, Honours, Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and ſuch like gifts of God; let them conſider, that in a little while, they muſt deſcend into the Grave, and then ſure their Haughty Spirits will be brought down and humbled: They muſt ſoon leave all their Worldly En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, and be laid in the duſt, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps be trampled on by thoſe very Men, who before they deſpiſed and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed:
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:63173:59"/>Why then is duſt and aſhes proud? Whoſoever is proud, let him go to the Vaults and Tombs of the Dead, he will there find no difference; nothing within but ſtench and rottenneſs; and let him conſider that of the Pſalmiſt; <hi>I have ſeen the Wicked in great power,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vidi potentes impios Gravique faſtu turgidos Vireſcere inſtar laureae Amaena propter fluminae. Specto repente, en lubricae Imago nuſquam gloriae, Nuſquam manens veſtigia Cunctis gravis potentiae.</hi> Buchanan in Pſ. 37.35, 36.</note> and ſpreading himſelf like a green Bay-tree: Yet he paſſed away, and Lo, he was not; yea, I ſought him, but he could not be found:</hi> And therefore according to the advice of <hi>Tobit: Love thy Brethren,
<note place="margin">Tob. 4.13.</note> and deſpiſe not in thy Heart thy Brethren, for in pride is deſtruction, and much trouble:</hi> This caſt <hi>Lucifer</hi> from Heaven: For <hi>God reſiſteth the Proud, and giveth grace to the Humble.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.5.</note> If thou ſhouldeſt find any thing in thy ſelf, for which others praiſe thee, ſay with the Apoſtle;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.10. Pſ. 115.1.</note> 
                  <hi>by the grace of God, I am what I am,</hi> and <hi>not unto us O Lord, not unto us, but unto thy Name, give glory.</hi> And, <hi>Lord I am not worthy of the leaſt of all thy Mercies: For what haſt thou that thou didſt not receive?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 32.10.</note> And ſince thou didſt receive from God all that thou haſt, it ſhould rather be an occaſion to humble thee, than to make thee proud: If you find any thing good
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:63173:59"/>in you, you ought to think that others are better, that ſo you may keep your ſelf humble; neither ſhall we be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted by our own, but by the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, who is oftentimes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with what we like very well; be not too curious in judging others, but rather turn your Eyes on your own ſelf: In judging others, one may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſtake, and very often ſin: But our labour will not be in vain, if we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine and judge our ſelves: Neither is it lawful for the Rich Men of this World, to be proud of their Wealth, and prodigally to ſpend it after their own Luſts: for they as well as others, are but Stewards of thoſe Riches which God hath committed to their Truſt, and the more they have, the more they muſt give an account of: And thus Holy <hi>David</hi> prayed when he was dying: <hi>All that is in the Heaven and in the Earth is thine: Thine is the Kingdom, and thou art exalted as Head above all:
<note place="margin">1 Chr. 29.11.</note> Both Riches and Honour come of thee:</hi> And by the Prophet <hi>Haggai,</hi> God ſays: <hi>The Silver is mine, and the Gold is mine:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hag. 2.8.</note> And if God gives them unto any one, it is not to make them haughty; or that they ſhould ſpend them prodigally,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:63173:60"/>but that the poor ſhould be partakers with them; be careful therefore not to be liſted up, or abuſe thy Riches and power; <hi>for a ſharp Judgment ſhall be to them that are in High places:
<note place="margin">Wiſd. 6.5, 6.</note> For Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy will ſoon pardon the meaneſt, but mighty Men ſhall be mightily tormented.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then againſt <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> let the Chriſtian Arm himſelf with this Conſideration of <hi>Job: Naked came I out of my Mothers Womb, and naked ſhall I return thither,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 1.21.</note> and with that of <hi>Solomon: As he came forth of his Mothers Womb, naked ſhall he return, to go as he came,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.15.</note> and ſhall take nothing of his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, which he may carry away in his hand.</hi> As alſo that of St. <hi>Paul; we brought nothing into this World,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.7.</note> and it is certain we can carry nothing out;</hi> let us not vainly deceive our ſelves with the Rich Man in the Goſpel, who ſaid to his Soul: <hi>Soul thou hast much goods laid up for many years,
<note place="margin">Luke 12.19.</note> take thine eaſe, Eat, Drink, and be Merry,</hi> leaſt we hear from God the ſame Sentence as he did; <hi>Thou fool,
<note place="margin">verſ. 20.</note> this night ſhall thy Soul be required of thee, then whoſe ſhall thoſe things be which thou haſt provided?</hi> Let us therefore always remember the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Advice;
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Tim. 6.8.</note> 
                  <hi>if we have food and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:63173:60"/>let us be therewith content:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Puer fui. nunc ſum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Ope deſtitutum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> Videre memini, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> Ejus petentes libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Buchauan. Pſ. 37.25.</note> And that of the Pſalmiſt: <hi>I have been young, and now am old, yet have I not ſeen the Righteous forſaken, nor his Seed begging Bread</hi> Remember alſo our Lords Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel; <hi>ſeek ye firſt the Kingdom of God,
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.33.</note> and his Righteouſneſs, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you: No Man can ſerve two Masters, God and Mammon:</hi> Did we but throughly conſider how much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and danger, and evil too, Riches bring with them, we ſhould not ſo greedily covet after them: The love and deſire of Mony is more vexatious, than the uſe thereof can be either plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or profitable; Riches are never got without trouble, and ſeldom with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinning againſt, and offending God; they are never kept without Care, nor loſt without Sorrow: What good hath the Richeſt Man in the World from all this Treaſures more than this, that he may live upon them? And ſince our lives are ſo very ſhort, what need is there for Hoarding up for ſo many years? At the end of our Lives, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of him that hath poſſeſſed but little, will not be worſe, but better than
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:63173:61"/>his that hath poſſeſſed much; for he hath had leſs trouble whilſt he liv'd, and hath a leſs account to give up when he is dead; what then, O Man, do thoſe things profit thee, which are good for nothing after thou art dead? Nor is there any need to ſcrape toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a great deal of wealth, that we may leave an Eſtate to our Children and Heirs; this indeed ſeems plauſible, and hath deceiv'd many: But who knows what our Heirs ſhall be, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thankful or ungrateful? And it is certain that great Riches left to Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, do more often prove the incite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and occaſions of Wickedneſs, than of Virtue: If any one diligently examined, what daily happens in the World, he would find, that very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny poor Mens Children did raiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Wealth and Eminency, and on the contrary, many Rich Mens Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren did prodigally ſpend the Eſtates left them by their Parents, and became miſerably poor: In ſhort therefore, godlineſs with contentment, is great gain.</p>
               <p>Another Vice the Chriſtian is to Arm himſelf againſt, is <hi>Luxury:</hi> Now to extinguiſh theſe exorbitant and unruly
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:63173:61"/>Luſts and Deſires of the Fleſh, and to hinder us from treating it with ſoftneſs and delicacy; let us often conſider that a little while hence, our Bodies will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſtinking Carkaſes: For what is our Fleſh, how finely ſoever it be treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cloathed, and fed, and pampered, but food for Worms? <hi>Luxury</hi> chiefly comprehends <hi>Luſt</hi> and <hi>Drunkenneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againſt <hi>Luſt</hi> a Chriſtian ought dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to fortifie himſelf: The prize of Chaſtity is of all the moſt difficult, the Conflict is perpetual, but the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory rare: Remember therefore what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays: <hi>Flee Fornication,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.18.</note> every ſin that a Man doth is without the Body, but he that committeth Fornication, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth against his own Body:</hi> Our Body is the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt, the Tabernacle into which is received the Holy Body and Blood of Chriſt: Take therefore the Advice of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 9. v. 7, 8.</note> Look not round about thee in the Streets of the City, neither wander thou in the Solitary places thereof: Turn away thine Eye from a Beautiful Woman, and look not upon anothers Beauty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> which is the other part of Luxury, is amongſt other Vices
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:63173:62"/>more eſpecially to be avoided, becauſe now a days it is by many thought no ſin, but rather accounted praiſe-worthy, although there be no plague more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to Chriſtianity, and nothing more ſeverely forbid than this:
<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>For the Drunkard regardeth not the work of the Lord, neither conſiders the operations of his Hands:
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.10.</note> Drunkards ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God:</hi> Wine and Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, captivates the Heart of Man, ſo that the Holy Spirit will no longer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide in him: It is very dangerous even to be once Drunk: For our Saviour adviſeth us to <hi>take heed to our ſelves, leaſt at any time our Hearts be overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with Surfeiting and Brunkenneſs,</hi> but to be ſober and to watch unto Prayer, becauſe the hour is uncertain when the Son of Man will come; we therefore ought always to keep our ſelves free from this ſin, becauſe we muſt appear before the Tribunal of Chriſt, in the ſame ſtate as we were in at the hour of Death; let every one therefore conſider what a terrible thing it would be for a Man whilſt he is Drunk, to be taken on a ſudden out of the Land of the living, by ſome unexpected fall, by the Sword, or ſome other Violence, or by
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:63173:62"/>a fit of an Apoplexy; and withal, let Drunkards conſider how many poor Chriſtians there are in the World, who would think themſelves happy, if they might have their fill of Bread and ſmall Drink, whilſt they ſo unjuſtly and laviſhly waſt the pretious gifts of God; let them beware, leaſt at laſt it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to them, as it did to that Rich Glutton, who when he had fared Sump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly every day, and denied poor <hi>Lazarus</hi> the crums that fell from his Table, he was buried in Hell, where not ſo much as a drop of water would be allowed him to cool his Tongue in thoſe infernal flames.</p>
               <p>And becauſe <hi>Idleneſs</hi> adminiſters the greateſt fuel to <hi>Luxury;</hi> therefore more eſpecially avoid idleneſs: Be always in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent about ſomething or other: Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, Read, Write, Pray, Work, or follow diligently the buſineſs of your particular Callings; and by theſe means the love of Pleaſures will be more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly damp'd and exſtinguiſhed.</p>
               <p>Another ſin we are to arm ourſelves againſt, is <hi>Envy,</hi> which is a diveliſh Vice, and according to ſome, was the cauſe of Satans fall, and which made him endeavour the overthrow of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind:
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:63173:63"/>Againſt this let us conſider, that all the good things we enjoy, are not from our ſelves, but are diſpenced and diſtributed amongſt us by the great Lord of all, as he ſees beſt: Why then, O Man, ſhouldſt thine Eye be evil, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is good and kind to thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour? It is rather thy Duty, when thou ſeeſt all things ſucceed well with thy Neighbour, to give thanks unto God, and to think that thou art not worthy of ſuch proſperity, or that it would not be profitable unto thee: Why ſhouldſt thou envy another thoſe things he poſſeſſeth without thy loſs or hurt? When as if he had them not, thou wouldſt not have them: Is it not a property of the Devil, when thou art by the juſt Judgment of God under any Miſery or Trouble, to wiſh that others were miſerable alſo? Laſtly, conſider what good envy doth; moſt certainly thou canſt not by it, trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thy Neighbours goods unto thy ſelf: Thou hurteſt thy ſelf only; whilſt thou breakeſt thy Heart with Vexation and Languiſh, thou art only thy own Tormentor and Executioner. After all, the moſt preſent Remedy for Envy, is to be Humble, to avoid Pride and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:63173:63"/>from whence Envy gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally proceeds: For whoever lives con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with his own condition, never envies the Honours and Riches of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men.</p>
               <p>And to name no more, the Chriſtian ought to fortifie his mind againſt, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Enmity, and Hatred, Slandering, and falſe accuſation,</hi> by conſidering that all the while a Man is out of Charity with his Neighbour, ſo long he is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceptable to God; inſomuch, that ſuch an one under the Old Teſtament, could offer no Sacrifice to God; and under the New, cannot ſay that Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which our Lord hath taught us: For thus our Saviour Admoniſheth us,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.23, 24.</note> 
                  <hi>If thou bring thy gift to the Altar, and there remembrest that thy Brother hath ought againſt thee; leave there thy gift, and go thy way, firſt be reconciled to thy Brother, and then come and offer thy gift:</hi> And in the Lords Prayer we Pray;
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Forgive us our Debts, as we forgive our Debtors,</hi> which is farther enforced at the end of the Prayer, by this reaſon, <hi>for if ye for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give Men their Treſpaſſes, your Heavenly Father will alſo forgive you:
<note place="margin">verſ. 14, 15.</note> But if ye forgive not Men their Treſpaſſes, neither will your Father forgive you.</hi> Let us
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:63173:64"/>alſo reflect on thoſe ſevere words of our Saviour:
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.22.</note> 
                  <hi>But I ſay unto you, that whoſoever is angry with his Brother with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cauſe, ſhall be in danger of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and whoſoever ſhall ſay to his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> Raca, <hi>ſhall be in danger of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, but whoſoever ſhall ſay, thou fool, ſhall be in danger of Hell fire:</hi> and in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place:
<note place="margin">Luk. 6.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Love your Enemies, do good to them which hate you:
<note place="margin">verſe 28.</note> Bleſs them that Curſe you, and pray for them which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitefully uſe you:
<note place="margin">verſe 31.</note> — And as ye would that Men ſhould do unto you, do ye alſo to them likewiſe,
<note place="margin">verſe 32.</note> for if ye love them which love you, what thank have ye? For ſinners alſo love thoſe that love them:
<note place="margin">verſe 35.</note> — But love ye your Enemies, and do good, and your reward ſhall be great, and ye ſhall be the Children of the Higheſt, for he is kind unto the unthankful, and to the evil.
<note place="margin">verſe 36.</note> Be ye therefore merciful, as your Father alſo is merciful.
<note place="margin">verſe 37.</note> Judg not, and ye ſhall not be Judged, Condemn not, and ye ſhall not be Condemned, Forgive, and ye ſhall be Forgiven.</hi> The Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons theſe amongſt the works of the Fleſh:
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.20, 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Hatred, Variance, Emulations, Wrath, Strife, Seditions, Envyings, and ſuch like,</hi> and pronounceth, <hi>that they which do ſuch things, ſhall not inherit the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:63173:64"/>Kingdom of God.</hi> And St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.14, 15.</note> 
                  <hi>He that loveth not his Brother, abideth in Death: Whoſoever hateth his Brother, is a Murderer.</hi> We have good reaſon to bear with the infirmities of others, becauſe there are many things which others muſt bear with in us: For no one is perfect: You ſee plainly, that you are not able to bring your ſelf to live accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thoſe Rules which you could wiſh, and why then ſhould you be angry with others, if they do not live juſt as you would have them?
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.5.</note> 
                  <hi>firſt caſt out the Beam out of thine own Eye, and then ſhalt thou ſee clearly to caſt out the Mote out of thy Brothers Eye;</hi> let us therefore <hi>bear one anothers Burthens,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6.2.</note> for there is no body without fault.</p>
               <p>And then farther let us endeavour to keep our ſelves from Slandering, and Calumniating of others, by not being too curious in enquiring into the Words, and Actions, and Lives of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; for what, O Man, is it to thee, what another ſays or does?
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Who art thou, that judgeſt another Mans Servant? To his own Maſter, he ſtandeth or falleth.</hi> Do thy beſt, to give a good account of thine own Words and Actions to God; and he alſo is obliged to render
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:63173:65"/>an account of his to the ſame God, to whom all things are naked and open; he ſees all things under the Sun, and knows what every one thinks and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and to what end they direct their Actions; therefore commit all to him, reſt contented, and do not diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et thy ſelf with others cares.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O Lord our moſt Merciful Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who in thy Son Jeſus Chriſt hath called me to Eternal Life, and forgiven me all my ſins, let thy Holy Spirit alſo direct and rule my heart, that I may daily perſevere in a true Repentance, continually ſtrive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my ſins, and increaſe more and more in all vertuous and godly living. And for as much as my own ſtrength is not ſufficient to contend againſt ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Enemies, and to bring my good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to effect, do thou, O Lord ſtretch forth thy Right Hand to aſſiſt me,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:63173:65"/>leaſt I ſaint in the Warfare, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan get the Dominion over me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thou, O Lord, reſiſteſt the Proud, but giveſt grace to the Humble: The proud in heart is an Abomination to thee, vouchſafe me therefore, O Lord, an humble Spirit, devoid of all High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindedneſs, according to the example of our Bleſſed Lord, who being in the form of God, humbled himſelf even to the Death of the Croſs, that he might exalt us unto everlaſting life: Make me to conſider that I am but Duſt and Aſhes, and have no reaſon to lift up my ſelf; let me not be proud of thoſe gifts which thou haſt beſtowed on me, and ſcornfully deſpiſe others, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that what ever good is in me, I have received it all from thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O Lord, naked came I out of my Mothers Womb, but thou haſt bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully given me, Meat and Drink, Cloathing and Habitation, and all things neceſſary for the preſervation of my
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:63173:66"/>life. Make me to be contented with my</hi> Daily Bread, <hi>that my mind may never be poſſeſs'd with Covetouſneſs: But may remember, that I muſt go out of this World naked as I came, and therefore may</hi> lay up my Treaſure in Heaven, <hi>which I may enjoy to all Eternity:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And becauſe I know that in me dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth no good thing, and the Fleſh always Luſteth againſt the Spirit, and is daily enticing me to the pleaſures of this World; grant O Lord, that by the aſſiſtance of thy Holy Spirit, I may crucifie and mortifie the Fleſh with its affections and Luſts, and may</hi> live ſoberly, righteonſly and godly in this preſent World, <hi>and ſerve thee in pureneſs of Spirit all the days of my life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Grant alſo, that according to thy command and example, we may love one another: Root out of our Hearts all bitterneſs and malice, that the</hi> Sun
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:63173:66"/>may never go down upon our Wrath, <hi>but that we may do good to thoſe that hate us, and forgive all that have offended us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord, I beſeech thee, take from me Pride, and give me the Spirit of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: Extinguiſh in me the deſires of the Fleſh, and inflame my Heart with the love of thee: Caſt out of my mind, the fury of anger, and implant therein the gift of Patience; Remove from me the love of Vain-glory, the bitterneſs of Envy; and beſtow on me the ſweetneſs of Charity and Humility, the gift of a</hi> meek and quiet Spirit, which is in thy ſight of great price.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:63173:67"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>A Diary of the practice of Piety.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUT for as much as the Exerciſes of Piety ought to be every day performed, becauſe no body can be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain which ſhall be that laſt day, when he ſhall depart out of this life, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day, for ought we know, may be our laſt: It will therefore be very uſeful to have both in our view and memory the courſe of one day regular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpos'd, according to the pattern whereof we may lead our lives, that ſo every day we may be prepared for an happy Death.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, O Man, when you awake out of ſleep in the Morning, let your earlieſt Meditations be on God, nor ever let any thing but the thoughts of God firſt enter into your mind: For ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Contemplations of God being once admitted into our minds, will keep out all evil Devices; think then firſt,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:63173:67"/>that God will eaſily hereafter raiſe you from the dead, as now you are awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken'd from your ſleep.</p>
               <p>Afterwards when with open'd eyes you behold the light of the Sun think with your ſelf, how great the Glory and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of the laſt day will be, when ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred thouſand glorious Bodies ſhining like the Sun and Stars, ſhall go with Chriſt their Judge, like ſo many Suns, into eternal life; and therefore uſe all diligence that you may appear one of that bleſſed number.</p>
               <p>Afterwards revolve in your mind, that <hi>the Devil, like a Roaring Lion,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8</note> walketh about, ſeeking whom he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour:</hi> That he was not far from you the night paſt, and had a deſire to hurt you, and could have done it, unleſs God had defended you by the Miniſtry of his Holy Angels: And withal, think that the Holy Angels were encamped all night round about you, that now you are riſing from your Bed, they ſtand by you, and therefore take care to behave your ſelf Circumſpectly, as being placed in the preſence of God and the bleſſed Angels.</p>
               <p>When you put on your Cloaths, think that they are the Tokens of guilt,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:63173:68"/>with which we cover our ſhame and nakedneſs, and therefore you have no cauſe to be proud of them: and whilſt you cover your Body, let not your Soul be naked, but put on the wedding Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, even the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt; and think how unſuitable it would be, to have a mind filthy and ſtained with ſin, under a fair and clean garment.</p>
               <p>Never undertake any buſineſs, unleſs you have firſt humbly compos'd your mind and body to Prayer: Thank God from your very heart, that he hath been pleaſed to preſerve you the laſt night, and even all your life, from the Snares and Violence of Satan, and to keep you and yours from all outward perils and dangers; and pray unto him, that he would mercifully forgive you all your ſins, for the Merits of Chriſt, that he would preſerve you and yours; all the faithful, and the univerſal Church, from the power and ſubtilty of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; that he would pleaſe to defend you from all dangers of Body and Soul, and ſo guide you by his Holy Spirit, that you may not offend him this day by any ſin; but that all your Thoughts, Words and Actions, may be directed to the glory of God, and the good of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:63173:68"/>Mankind; that he will pleaſe not to take you out of the World unprepared by a ſudden death; and that if he ſhould think it fitting to take away your life this very day, he would be merciful unto you, and receive you to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <p>Every Morning renew your reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſerving God, and as if this were the firſt day of your returning to God, and that hitherto you had done no kind of good, firmly purpoſe in your mind, to love the Lord your God, and ſerve him only: And humbly pray un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, that he would pleaſe to keep and aſſiſt you in theſe your good Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of ſerving him. In the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, adviſe with your ſelf what you are to do that day; in the Evening take an account of what you have done: And that you may have comfort at night, ſtedfaſtly determine to ſpend the day well.</p>
               <p>Having offer'd up your prayers to God, read a Chapter or two in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, and attentively conſider, what there is contained in it for your Conſolation, or Inſtruction, or Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: From the Sacred Hiſtory you may obſerve, how great Gods anger is
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:63173:69"/>againſt ſins, and with what terrible plagues he hath puniſh'd ſinners; and on the contrary, with what ſignal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he hath recompenced Holineſs, and how wonderfully he hath condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted his own People. In ſhort, ſo read the Scriptures, as thereby to confirm your Faith, and excite in you the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Piety. Do the ſame alſo at night when you are going to Bed, and thus in no long ſpace of time, you will have read over the whole Bible, and ſo will be provided with a ſure guide in the paths of Virtue all the days of your life. As Holy <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Thy Word is a Lamp unto my Feet,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 119.105.</note> and a Light unto my Path. The Law of the Lord is perfect,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 19.8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> converting the Soul: The Teſtimony of the Lord is ſure, making Wiſe the ſimple. The Statutes of the Lord are right, rejoycing the Heart; the Commandment of the Lord is pure, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning the Eyes. The fear of the Lord is clean, enduring for ever: The Judgments of the Lord are true, and righteous all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. More to be deſired are they than Gold, yea, than much fine Gold: Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er alſo than Hony, and the Hony Comb. Moreover by them is thy Servant warned, and in keeping of them there is great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:63173:69"/>
               <p>Be careful therefore not to read the Holy Scriptures out of Cuſtom only, and as it were by the by, but ſtay a while in the Meditation of what you have read; for there is no Chapter but will yield very profitable matter for Holy Contemplations, to wit, on the Wiſdom of God, his Omnipotency, Infinity, Goodneſs, Mercy, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: On the Corruption of Humane Nature; our own ſins; the Snares and Temptations of the Devil; the pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhments of the Wicked, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of the Righteous; on the frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſhortneſs and mortality of Humane Nature: On Repentance; Faith; the exerciſe of Holineſs: On our Bleſſed Saviours Incarnation, Nativity, Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Paſſion, Death, Reſurrection, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention, Interceſſion, and his Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mankind: On the laſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Happy State of the Bleſſed in the life to come, and the miſery of the Damned in Hell.</p>
               <p>Theſe and the like, as they offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, are to be heedfully attended to, and ſome time Meditated upon, until ſome ſorrow of Mind, ſome ardor of Devotion, ſome act of Faith, ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine flame of love ſprings up in your Soul:</p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:63173:70"/>
               <p>Having thus performed your Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, from which never ſuffer your ſelf to be withdrawn by any thing whatever, ſince there is nothing ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and weighty, as to be preferr'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, you may then apply your ſelf to the Duties of your Calling with a full intention to diſcharge them faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; for the due performance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, you are not only diligently to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of offending God, either in Thought, Word or Deed, and of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring your Neighbour, but you ought alſo to direct all your Actions to Gods glory, and the good of others.</p>
               <p>Firſt, as to what concerns your thoughts; although the godly by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Corruption of Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, cannot avoid all evil thoughts, yet be careful leaſt you too much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge them, but ſuppreſs them betimes, and be ſure never to bring them forth to act, nor ſuffer your ſelf to be ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in your Affections to any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Honeſty and Piety, and which may in the leaſt alienate your mind from the happineſs of the life Eternal: Never ſeek after popular Fame: Be not Ambitious after Honours, Riches, or any Worldly thing, but more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:63173:70"/>do not prefer them before God; be humble, and contented with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency, and a good Conſcience; he is very happy, and hath every thing, who hath God for his Friend: He is moſt miſerable, and hath nothing who hath God for his Enemy: When ever any ſinful affections begin by little and little to ſteal into your mind, as Avarice, Voluptuouſneſs, Envy, Anger, Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Hatred, and ſuch like, as we have before mentioned in the precede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chapter, be diligent to ſtifle them in their firſt motions.</p>
               <p>As to what concerns your words and diſcourſe, ſo govern your ſelf, as always remembring that ſevere expreſſion of our Lords;
<note place="margin">Mat. 12.36.</note> 
                  <hi>That every idle word that Men ſhall ſpeak, they ſhall give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thereof in the day of Judgment.</hi> And therefore in your jeſting, obſerve, never to caſt a blot upon Religion, or Scandalize any one, or offend againſt the Rules of Honeſty and Modeſty: So order all your Speech, that you never Scandalize your Neighbour, but endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to build him up in the moſt Holy Faith; to this end pray with <hi>David: Set a Watch, O Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 141.3.</note> and keep the Door of my Lips.</hi> There is no
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:63173:71"/>true joy, but what is joyned with the love of God, and a good Conſcience, We often laugh, when if the great danger we are in were rightly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, there is more need we ſhould weep; let your words and your Heart go together, and let both always agree with truth; avoid lying, and deſraud none with deceitful words; when ever you ſpeak of God, or Holy things, do it reverently and diſcreetly, and take not the name of God in vain; ſpeak ill of no body, neither maliciouſly ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any perſon whatever.</p>
               <p>And then as to your Life and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, commit your ways unto God, and whatever you take in hand, begin it in his Name, and do all to the glory of God. What ever you are about to do, think firſt, whether you would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of it, if another did it: For why ſhould you do your ſelf, what you would not like in another? What ever you hear and ſee another ſpeak or do that is good and praiſe-worthy, do you endeavour to imitate it: But if you obſerve any one to do things for which he deſerves to be blam'd, beware leaſt you do the like: Moreover conſider whether you can give a good account
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:63173:71"/>of what you are going to do before the great Judge at the laſt Day: Your own Conſcience will be a better Judge of your Actions, than all the World; and although Men are ignorant of what you do, yet remember that God ſees you, and that you can do nothing ſo privately, but your own Conſcience will be a Witneſs and a Judge of it.</p>
               <p>In the duties of your calling truſt in God, nor ever attempt to diſcharge them by unlawful means which God hath forbidden: Never think any thing gainful or expedient, which may in the leaſt hinder the Salvation of your Soul. Do what is right and juſt, and never prefer the praiſe of Men, before the favour of God; if God be gracious to you, be not concern'd though the World hate you: In ſhort, let this be your conſtant rule, to direct all your actions to the glory of God, and to the good and profit of your Neighbour, ſo that whatever offends againſt this, forbear it, however goodly and ſpecious it may appear. In all your Converſation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have your ſelf as becomes a faithful Servant, that you may one day hear that joyful voice of God,
<note place="margin">Mat. 25.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Well done thou good and faithful Servant, thou haſt
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:63173:72"/>been faithful over a few things, I will make thee Ruler over many things; enter thou into the joy of thy Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When you are about to eat or drink, pray for Gods Bleſſing on it, that it may ſucceed to the health of your Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; and take ſo much as may ſuffice for the ſatisfying of your hunger and thirſt; after you have done, render thanks unto God for all his gifts and graces beſtowed on you, and deſire his bleſſing may go along with them: And when your Body is full, take care, that your Soul be not empty, but beg that it may be repleniſh'd with the Grace of God:</p>
               <p>All the day long, whatever your Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment be, lift up your Heart unto God in frequent and ſhort Ejaculations, rendring him thanks for all his benefits, and commending you and yours to his Protection and Governance.</p>
               <p>On Holy-Days, or any others ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Church for Prayers or hearing Gods Word, let no buſineſs ever detain you from joyning your Prayers with thoſe of the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the obtaining publick and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Bleſſings from God, ſince our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour hath promiſed his gracious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:63173:72"/>where two or three are gathered together in his Name.</p>
               <p>It is alſo requiſite towards our dying Happily, that we frequently receive the Holy Supper of our Lord, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other Fruits of this Divine Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, we may be Admoniſhed of our Union with Chriſt, and ſo be fortified againſt the fears of Death; for altho' our Bodies putrifying in the Grave, or be any other ways diſſolv'd, yet is there no danger of our being ſeparated from Chriſt, with whom we are made one by the Bond of the Holy Spirit, but when we are dead, we ſtill remain uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him both in Body and Soul, and in the laſt day, when our Bodies ſhall be again joyned unto our Souls, they will ariſe unto Eternal Glory; for it is not poſſible that our Bodies ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in their Graves, when they are united to the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Moreover for as much as none can be certain of the hour of their Death, nor promiſe themſelves to morrow, and that on our laſt hour depends our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal State, and that after Death, we ſhall be tranſlated either to the joys of Heaven, or to the everlaſting Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:63173:73"/>of Hell; it is therefore our great concern to be always thinking of that hour, on which depends our Eternal Happineſs or Miſery: He is a prudent Man, who thinks that every hour may be the laſt hour of his life: Such a one will not eaſily fall into notorious ſins, but will uſe the things of this life thrif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, and look upon them as vain and tranſitory: But this cannot be done without Gods aſſiſtance, ſo that it will be very fitting as you regard your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Salvation, to pour out your Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers unto God with Ardent affections for his direction and aſſiſtance in ſuch a form as is at the end of this Chapter, or any other that ſuits your Devotion.</p>
               <p>When the day is finiſhed before you go to ſleep, be ſure you never omit to examine your own Conſcience; which judging of the Conſcience, being a thing ſo very uſeful, was even by the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then much approv'd of, ſo that it will be a ſhame for Chriſtians to come behind them in the ſtudy of Vertue, and will hereafter be very dangerous. <hi>Pythagoras</hi> hath deſcribed this Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Conſcience in very ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Verſes; the ſenſe whereof is, that at night before we compoſe our ſelves
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:63173:73"/>to reſt, we ought to call to mind the Actions of the day paſt, and chiefly to enquire into three things: what we have done? what we have leſt undone? and wherein we have tranſgreſſed our Duty? and as we find our actions to have been, accordingly we are to behave our ſelves, to be griev'd and diſpleas'd with our ſelves, for what we have done amiſs, and to take delight in what we have done well:</p>
               <p>This Examination of the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Seneca</hi> did not omit even amongſt the Noiſe and Diſtractions oſ the Court: <hi>I uſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>this Authority,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>or hae p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>teſtate &amp; quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die apud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e cauſam dico, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> ſublatum Conſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>e lumen eſt, conticu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> conſeta, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>ium <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> ſirutor fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> remeti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> ſemdo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> enim: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> mels <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> cere; vide, ne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> ſaclas, nunc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> Lib. 3. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> and daily plead my cauſe with my ſelf; when the light is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from my ſight, and my Wife is ſilent, being now inured to this cuſtom, I examine with my ſelf the whole day paſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view all that I have ſaid or done: I hide nothing from my own Seru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny, I paſs by nothing; for why ſhould I fear any thing by reaſon of my Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors? When as I can ſay, ſee that thon do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t it no more, and for this time I will pardon thee.</hi> Much more neceſſary then will it be for thee, O Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>an, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal to your mind every day what things
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:63173:74"/>you have done, and compare them with what you did the day before; when Evening comes to ſummon your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to Judgment; to ſet in order the miſcarriages of the day paſt, to ſee what things you have omitted, that you ought to have done, what you are to do the day following, and what you are to beware of: Nor is this a buſineſs of ſmall importance: For although our ſleep may be quiet and pleaſing without it, yet it can never be ſafe. He only reſts ſecurely, that is reconciled unto his God, and hath adjuſted his accounts with him, ſo that whether he dies in the Night, or awakens in the Morning, he is ſure to have God propitious to him: But it is moſt impudent raſhneſs, moſt pernicious preſumption, to indulge your ſelf in ſleep, whilſt your Soul is defiled with guilt; your Conſcience wounded in the day by ſin: And not made ſound again by Repentance: For ſhould death ſeize on you in your ſleep, before you are reſtor'd to Gods favour by Repentance, whether will your Soul go? they therefore very fooliſhly conſult their own Welfare, who ſpend the Evening in Drunkenneſs and Jolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and when they are ſatiated with
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:63173:74"/>Wine and Mirth, and reſt invites them, they go the next way to their beds, and are ſoon quite overcome with ſleep: Such precipitancy as this, is moſt deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate madneſs. If therefore you would have your ſleep quiet, and without fear, firſt examine your own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, bring to your remembrance the Divine Favours; if you have done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good that day, rejoyce and give God the glory, but if any evil, bewail it, beg Gods Pardon for your ſins, and firmly reſolve to live better for the future: But if you do not not daily follow this courſe, and that not negligently, but with care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, the ſame ſins, after divers months and years are paſt, will ſtill live and thrive in you: Whereas on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſuch an examination of the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is a powerful incitement to vertue; he who daily examins himſelf, neither deſires others praiſes, nor ſtands in need of their Admonitions or Reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: He doth not ſeek aſter the praiſe of Men, but he hath the applauſes of his own Conſcience; <hi>for</hi> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Our Rejoycing is this,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.12.</note> the Teſtimony of our Conſcience:</hi> And thoſe Reproo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which he doth not hear from others, he
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:63173:75"/>hath within from himſelf. There is no one ſo cautions, who doth not daily ſometimes forget himſelf, allowing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf too much liberty, or falling into the ſnares of Paſſion, Idleneſs, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Vice: Now in the Evening, it is in his own power to recover his ſteps, and again ſet himſelf free from the cruel Bondage of ſin: And thus every day reproving and correcting himſelf for his Errours, he will at length utterly extirpate the whole Body of ſin in him. When ever you find your ſelf to have tranſgreſſed <hi>(for there is no Man that ſinneth not)</hi> if you have not time for more, yet devoutly and from you heart ſay, <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner. Have mercy upon me, O God, after thy great goodneſs, according to the multitude of thy mercies, do away mine offences.</hi> But if you neglect this Examination, and huſh your Conſcience to ſleep, whilſt it is grieved, and guilty of ſin, and out of favour with God, you are ruin'd, and for ever undone, if this night ſhould be your laſt; and what ſecurity have you for your life one night longer? Now he frees himſelf from theſe dangers, who ſearches diligently into his own Soul, before he betakes himſelf to reſt,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:63173:75"/>endeavours to appeaſe his offended God, by a lively Faith and ſincere Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, through the Merits of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, for ſhould his Soul even that night be taken away from him, yet would he die well and happily: And more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, if by any Temptation, you ſhould be drawn aſide to ſtrife and contentions with your Neighbour, do not ſuffer <hi>the Sun to go down upon your Wrath,</hi> but be reconciled unto him, <hi>and forgive him, even as God for Chriſts ſake hath forgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Furthermore it is neceſſary before you go to ſleep, that you read ſome portion of the Holy Scriptures, and then humbly return thanks to God for all the Mercies and Benefits of the day paſt, and pray unto him, that he would mercifully forgive you all your ſins, by which you have ſo grievouſly offended him; that he would pleaſe to preſerve you the following night from the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and wiles of Satan, and from all perils and dangers of Soul and Body; and with your ſelf commend all yours, and all faithful Chriſtians to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of God.</p>
               <p>When you put off your Cloaths, bethink your ſelf that the time will
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:63173:76"/>ſurely come, and that for ought you know very ſpeedily, when you muſt for ever leave all things in this World.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, When you lay you down in your bed, let it put you in mind of your Grave, in which your body is to ſleep till the day of Judgment; let your bed mind you of the Earth that is to cover you; your Cloaths, your Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sheet in which when dead, you are to be wrapt; and let your approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſleep mind you of Death it ſelf: And as you deſire to awake ſafe, and in good health in the Morning, ſo deſire of God, that you may joyfully ariſe our of your Grave at the laſt day, and may with good aſſurance ſtand before the Throne of Chriſt our Judge; and at laſt when you are going to ſleep ſay; <hi>I will lay me down in peace,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 4. ult.</note> and take my reſt, for it is thou Lord, only that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt me dwell in ſafety.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O Eternal and moſt gracious God, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who haſt been pleaſed
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:63173:76"/>mercifully to preſerve me in ſafety to this preſent day, and haſt defended me from the violence of Satan, let thy Holy Spirit direct and rule me in all my ways, that I may know how frail I am, how few and evil the days of the years of my life are, that ſo I may apply my heart unto Wiſdom: Forgive me, I beſeech thee, all the ſins which from my Child-hood until now, I have committed againſt thee, by Thought Word and Deed, and by omitting to do thoſe good things which thou haſt commanded me to perform. Have mercy upon me, O God, according to thy loving kindneſs; according to the multitude of thy tender mercies, blot out my Tranſgreſſions: And enter not into Judgment with thy Servant, O Lord, for in thy ſight ſhall no Man living be juſtified: And grant, O Lord, that I may ſpend the remaining part of my time in working out my own Salvation with fear and trembling, doing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:63173:77"/>ſuch things as are well pleaſing in thy ſight: O let the thoughts of death be continually in my mind: O let the apprehenſions of that ſtrict account which I muſt make before thee at the laſt day, deter me from Tranſgreſſing thy Laws, that I may ſo ſpend every day and hour of my life, as if they were the laſt I had to live. Eſtabliſh in me a full purpoſe of mind, to direct all my Thoughts, Words and Actions to the glory of thy Holy Name: The good of my Neighbour, and the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Welfare of my own Soul. O let me not dare to ſin againſt thee, for the ſake of any thing in the World, but grant that with a conſtant reſolution of ſerving and pleaſing thee, and by a lively Faith in our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, I may be always provided for an happy departure out of this life. Ah! Merciful Lord, let not a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den death overtake me unawares, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nable me to War a good Warfare, to
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:63173:77"/>keep Faith and a good Conſcience, that ſo whereſoever or whenſoever it ſhall pleaſe thee to call for me out of this World, I may follow thee chearfully, and without delay, and joyfully ſtand before the Tribunal of my Redeemer Jeſus Chriſt, and receive that Crown of Righteouſneſs, which is laid up for all thoſe that love his appearing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O Father of mercies, and God of all Conſolation, let thy Holy Spirit ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver depart from me, eſpecially when I am yielding up the Ghoſt, but vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe me his Divine help and Aſſiſtance, to vanquiſh all the difficulties of this World, and all the Temptations of the Fleſh and the Devil: Grant me grace to fix my mind on nothing but thee, thy goodneſs and mercy, and to put my Truſt and Confidence in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone Merits of thy Son our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to the laſt breath of my life, and then, O Lord, receive my Soul. Into thy hands I commend my Spirit, O
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:63173:78"/>Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt; O Bleſſed Trinity, O Eternal Unity, ſave and defend me in this life, and at the hour of Death, O do not leave me, nor forſake me.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>Of the more ſpecial and particular pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for Death.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving now treated of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral preparation for Death, which is to be performed the whole courſe of our life, even whilſt we are young, and in our greateſt health and vigour: We now come to that more ſpecial and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular preparation, which is neceſſary to be done, when we are worn out with old Age, or taken with any ſudden and dangerous Diſeaſe, ſo that we think the time of our departure is at hand: For Death, when we look on it at a diſtance only, doth not much affect us; but when we find it making its approaches
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:63173:78"/>near us, we are then very penſive, and diſturb'd with the thoughts of it. When ever therefore, O Man, any Diſeaſe ſeizeth on you, think that ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is the Harbinger of Death, and that you are now admoniſhed from Heaven, as <hi>Hezechiah</hi> once was by the Prophet; to <hi>ſet thine Houſe in order,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 38.2.</note> for thou ſhalt die.</hi> And rather look for Death than life: For the event of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is very uncertain, though at firſt it may ſeem but a light indiſpoſition; and it often happens that the Diſeaſe gaining more and more ſtrength, doth unexpectedly deprive a Man of the uſe of his Reaſon, and of all ſerious Thoughts: So that as ſoon as ever you find your ſelf ill, prepare your ſelf for Death; for if you ſhould ſoon be well again, yet your Care and Labour would not be in vain; but if Death ſhould come upon you before you are provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for it, you run the hazard of loſing your Soul for ever;
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note> 
                  <hi>For it is appointed unto Men once to die, but after this the Judgment:</hi> It is a moſt falſe and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh opinion which hath obtained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſome, that the ſick perſon will moſt certainly die, if he makes his Will, and receives the Sacrament of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:63173:79"/>the Body and Blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: This hath, no doubt, been ſuggeſted by the Devil, and ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad by ill Men, that by this means they might frighten Men from fitting themſelves for an happy Death.</p>
               <p>Now this pre-paration conſiſts in two parts, the firſt thereof reſpects the dying Man, and the other his Neighbour.</p>
               <p>As to the firſt; the dying Man is to take great care to reconcile himſelf to God, whom he hath offended; and to arm himſelf againſt all thoſe Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, which uſually happen at that time: To this end it will be neceſſary for him, to ſearch into his own Heart, and examine over his whole life from the beginning, to confeſs and bewail all his ſins to God, to pour out moſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Prayers and Sighs by the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the Holy Spirit, for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining pardon of his ſins, and Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with God in Chriſt our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; Examples of ſuch Prayers may be found in the Penitential Pſalms, the prayer of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> and the like.</p>
               <p>And although the ſick Man ought chiefly to conleſs his ſins to God, againſt whom they were committed, yet it is fit, by the advice of the Apoſtle St.
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:63173:79"/>
                  <hi>James,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">James 5.16.</note> that he ſhould confeſs his faults to his Brethren; to the Miniſters of the Church and word of God, to whom Chriſt hath committed the keys of binding and abſolving: Of remitting and retaining ſins. And chiefly let him confeſs thoſe Crimes which moſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble his mind, and with which Satan moſt diſquiets him, ſuch let him repoſe in their Boſoms, who are ready to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him, and to Adminiſter ſuitable Conſolations; for ſick Mens minds are many times not ſedate enough for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Thoughts and Meditations, and the Devil is very ready to divert thoſe that offer themſelves: 'Tis therefore the part of the Miniſter of Gods Word, and his Friends to pray for the ſick perſon, that he may obtain pardon of his ſins, and not be overcome by the Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Devil.</p>
               <p>It often happens, that when Satan cannot drive Men to deſpair, he then puts on another diſguiſe, and puffs them up with an opinion of their Merits: This Temptation is diligently to be withſtood: For Satan exalteth thoſe, whom before he could not ſink down, that ſo he may caſt them headlong with a more grievous fall: Therefore O
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:63173:80"/>Man, if ever ſuch thoughts as theſe flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thee; conſider that it is owing to Gods grace, and not to your ſelf, if you are innocent from ſuch and ſuch offences, and remember how many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ways you have offended him: Or if you have been diligent in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of many good deeds, and theſe come into your mind, ſay with the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.10.</note> 
                  <hi>By the grace of God I am what I am, it was not I, but the grace of God which was with me.
<note place="margin">Pſ. 115.1.</note> And, not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but unto thy Name give glory:</hi> Remember that Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Saviour:
<note place="margin">Luk. 17.10.</note> 
                  <hi>When ye ſhall have done all thoſe things which are commanded you, ſay, we are unprofitable Servants; we we have done that which was our duty to do.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Eph. 1.8.</note> And that of St. <hi>John if we ſay that we have no ſin, we deceive ourſelves, and the truth is not in us.</hi> As alſo that of St.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vae omni lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili vitae homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, ſi remota miſericordiâ eam diſcutias, Domine.</hi> Conſ. lib. 9. Cap. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtin: Wo to the most perfect life of Man, if thou, Lord, ſhouldeſt lay aſide thy mercy, and examine it:</hi> If we read the Hiſtories of dying Men, or the advice and Counſel which the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt Men have given to ſuch as were ready to depart this life, we ſhall find them all have recourſe to that of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid:
<note place="margin">Pſ. 143.2.</note> Enter not into Judgment with thy
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:63173:80"/>Servant O Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 130.3.</note> for in thy ſight ſhall no Man living be juſtified: If thou, Lord, ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt make iniquities, O Lord, who ſhall ſtand?</hi> The beſt Men in the World when they have been in the agonies of Death, have begg'd earneſtly of God, for the Remiſſion of their ſins; nor could they expect or deſire Salvation from any, but only from our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; <hi>for there is none other Name under Heaven given among Men, whereby we muſt be ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Man thus ſeriouſly reconciled to God, will eaſily ſtruggle with, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all the Temptations which are wont to preſs in upon dying perſons: For although the remembrance of all the ſins of your paſt life, and thoſe too aggravated by the malice of Satan, and with all, the rigour of the laſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the ſeverity of the Judge, ſhould come into your mind; yet to theſe Terrours you may oppoſe, the Mercies of God the Father, the Merits of Jeſus Chriſt, and the moſt aſſured promiſes of forgiveneſs of ſins, which, as you ought always, and in your great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt health to remember, as hath been ſaid before, ſo, when Death approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, you ought more eſpecially to have
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:63173:81"/>them in a readineſs, the principal whereof are contained in theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Texts of Scripture:
<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Though your ſins be as Scarlet, they ſhall be as white as Snow,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 43.25.</note> though they be red like Crimſon, they ſhall be as Wool. I even I, ſaith the Lord, am he that blotteth out thy Tranſgreſſions for my own ſake, and will not remember thy ſins.
<note place="margin">Iſa. 55.7.</note> Let the wicked forſake his way, and the unrighteous Man his thoughts, and let him return unto the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him, and to our God, for he will abundantly Pardon:
<note place="margin">Zek. 18.32.</note> I have no pleaſure in the Death of him that dieth, ſaith the Lord God; wherefore turn your ſelves, and live ye. As I live ſaith the Lord God,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 33.11.</note> I have no pleaſure in the Death of the Wicked, but that the wicked turn from his way and live. Thou Lord art a God full of compaſſion and gracious:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 86.15.</note> Long ſuffering and plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in Mercy and Truth.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 147.3.11.</note> The Lord heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the broken in Heart, and bindeth up their Wounds. The Lord taketh pleaſure in them that fear him, in thoſe that hope in his Mercy.
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 1.7. Mat. 18.11.</note> The Blood of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſin. The Son of Man came to ſave that which was loſt. This is a faithful ſaying,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.15.</note> and worthy of all acceptation, that Jeſus Christ came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:63173:81"/>the World to ſave Sinners, of whom I am chief.
<note place="margin">1 Joh 2.2.</note> He is the propitiation for our ſins, and for the ſins of the whole World: Whoſoever liveth and believeth in him,
<note place="margin">John 11.26.</note> ſhall never die</hi> Eternally:
<note place="margin">John 1.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold the Lamb of God, which taketh away the ſins of the World:
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.28.</note> He ſhed his Blood for the Remiſſion of ſins.
<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.5.</note> He was wounded for our Tranſgreſſions, he was bruiſed for our iniquities: He that believeth on him, ſhall not be Condemned.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.33, &amp;c.</note> Who ſhall lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to the charge of Gods Elect? It is God that juſtifieth. Who is he that Condemneth? It is Chriſt that died, yea rather that is riſen again, who is even at the right Hand of God, who alſo maketh Interceſſion for us. Who ſhall ſeparate us from the love of Chriſt? Shall Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Diſtreſs,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.9.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord is long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering to us ward, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to Repentance;
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.4, &amp;c.</note> He would have all Men to be ſaved, and to come unto the knowledge of the Truth: For there is one God, and one Mediatour between God and Men, the Man Christ Jeſus: Who gave himſelf a Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom for all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You are therefore in no wiſe to doubt of the Mercies of God, and of the forgiveneſs of your ſins; for the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:63173:82"/>Mercies of God are infinitely greater than the ſins of all Mankind: It is an Article of our Chriſtian Faith, <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the forgiveneſs of ſins:</hi> So that <hi>if we confeſs our ſins, God is faithful and juſt to forgive us our ſins, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſs.</hi> Our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour invites all ſinners unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the kindeſt expreſſions; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<note place="margin">Matth. 11.28. Joh. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Come unto me all ye that are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt. For God ſo loved the World, that he gives his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth on him, ſhould not periſh, but have ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life:
<note place="margin">Joh. 5.24.</note> Verily I ſay unto you, he that heareth my word, and believeth on him that ſent me, hath everlaſting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation, but is paſſed from death unto life. He that believeth in me, though he were dead, yet ſhall he live.
<note place="margin">Joh. 6.35. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> I am the bread of life; he that cometh to me, ſhall never hunger, and he that believeth on me, ſhall never thirſt: All that the Father giveth me, ſhall come to me, and him that cometh to me, I will in no wiſe caſt out. And this is the Father's will, which hath ſent me, that of all which he hath given me, I ſhould loſe nothing, but ſhould
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:63173:82"/>raiſe it up again at the laſt day. And this is the will of him that ſent me, that every one which ſeeth the Son and believeth on him, may have everlaſting life, and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day. My ſheep bear my voice, and I know them,
<note place="margin">Joh. 10.27, 28.</note> and they follow me. And I give unto them elernal life, and they ſhall never periſh, neither ſhall any pluck them out of my hand. For I am perſwad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d that neither death, nor life, nor angels,
<note place="margin">Rom 8.</note> nor principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor an other creature, ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God, which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi> And every one that is grieved for his ſin, may ſay to himſelf, as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> heretofore ſaid to the Keeper of the Priſon at <hi>Philippi, Believe on the Lord Jeſus Christ, and thou ſhalt be ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it ſhould happen that your mind ſhould be diſturb'd with ſuch thoughts as theſe, that though Chriſt perhaps made ſatisfaction for ſome, yet ſure not for all, nor for grievous ſins; let ſome of the ſame conſolations be ready at hand: As theſe, <hi>the blood of Jeſus Christ cleanſeth us from all ſin. If
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:63173:83"/>any man ſin,
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 1.7.</note> we have an advocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous, and he is the propitiation for the ſins of the whole world.
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.1, 2. 1 Tim. 2.6.</note> He gave himſelf a ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom for all. Come unto me all ye that labour,
<note place="margin">Joh. 1.29.</note> and I will give you reſt. Behold the Lamb of God, which taketh away the ſins of the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that your ſorrow for your ſins may not exclude all hopes of mercy, call to mind the examples of many grievous ſinners, who obtain'd pardon from God;
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 11. 2 King. 21.</note> ſuch were <hi>David,</hi> a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer and an Adulterer: <hi>Manaſſes</hi> a very great ſinner:
<note place="margin">Matth. 26.</note> the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> who denied Chriſt:
<note place="margin">Luk. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Matthew,</hi> a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican, ſitting at the receit of cuſtom: <hi>Zacheus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 19. Joh. 8.</note> which was the chief among the publicans. <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> a ſinner and an adultreſs: the thief on the croſs: the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> a perſecutor of Chriſt, who writes thus of himſelf; <hi>This is a faithful ſaying and worthy of all acception, that Chriſt Jeſus came into the world to ſave ſinners, of whom I am chief: Howbeit for this cauſe I obtained mercy, that in me first, Jeſus Chriſt might ſhew forth all long-ſuffering, for a pattern to them which ſhould hereafter believe on him to life everlasting.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:63173:83"/>
               <p>But if you ſhould ſtill be tempted to think that you are a grievous ſinner, and that therefore your ſorrow for your ſins cannot be ſufficient to obtain your pardon: againſt this temptation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that the greatneſs of the Divine Mercy is not founded in your ſorrow, but in the merits of Chriſt: and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what our Lord ſaith,
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.28, 29.</note> 
                  <hi>Come unto me all that labour and are heavy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and I will reſreſh you, and ye ſhall find rest unto your ſouls:</hi> and,
<note place="margin">Joh. 9 37.</note> 
                  <hi>Him that cometh unto me, I will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi> To this purpoſe St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaks very well:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ne ſuae confidas paenitenti ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a namque paenitentia, tanta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit peccata delere, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſola foret poenitentia, jure timeres: Sed poſtquam cum paenitentia commiſcetur Dei miſericordia, conſide, quontam vicit tuam nequitiam. Multum enim eſt miſericors Deus, &amp; tantum clemens, ut neque filio peper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerit, ut ingratos ſervos reai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meret.</hi> Hom. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d Popul.</note> 
                  <hi>Do not rely on your own repentance: for alas your repentance can never blot out ſo many ſins: if you had nothing to trust to but your own re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, you might well be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid: But for as much as the mercy of God is joyn'd to your repentance, be of good courage, for that hath overcome your wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs: For God is very gracious, and ſo merciful, that he hath not ſpared his own Son, that he might Redeem his ungrateful Servants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any objection ſhould diſturb you of a partial Redemption, or of Gods
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:63173:84"/>abſolute Decrees, let his univerſal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, confirmed by an Oath comfort you.
<note place="margin">Iſa. 53 6. Col. 1.19, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>God hath laid on Chriſt the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of us a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l: It hath pleaſed the Father by Chriſt to reconcile all things unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:
<note place="margin">Tit 2.14. Joh. 3.16.</note> Christ gave himſelf for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity. So God loved the World, that whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth in his Son,
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.2.</note> ſhould not periſh. He is the propitiation for the ſins of the whole World.
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.9.</note> The Lord is long ſuffering, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to Repentance He would have all Men to be ſaved: There is one God, and one Mediator between God and Men, the Man Chriſt Jeſus; who gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Ranſom for all.</hi> Seek then for your Election in Chriſt, and do not frighten your ſelf with any abſolute Decrees of Reprobation; ſince the Father with an Oath, the Son with Tears, and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt by the voice of the Apoſtles have all teſtified, that they deſire the Salvation of all, even of thoſe that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: It is your part not to hinder the workings of the Holy Spirit by the Word and Sacraments, either by obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately refuſing his grace, when it is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd you; or maliciouſly caſting it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, when it is confer'd; ſo ſhall ye
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:63173:84"/>be certain for the future, of the love of God towards you, through the Merits of Chriſt received by Faith, and cannot doubt of your Election.</p>
               <p>And now do not by any means mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt the grace of God, but confirm and ſtrengthen your Faith by receiving the Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt: For when you ſpiritually eat the Body of Chriſt, and drink his Blood, you may be aſſured, that you are thereby made a partaker of all the benefits which Chriſt purchaſed for you on the Croſs by his torn Body, and his Blood poured out, and that now, by the ſatisfaction of Chriſt, you are in favour with God, have your ſins pardon'd, and have received the earneſt of Eternal Life and Salvation. This Divine Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet is <hi>the Medicine of Immortality, the Antidote againſt Death, the preſervative of life in God, through Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Ep. 11. ad Eph. Iſa. 42.3.</note> as <hi>Ignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſpeaks:</hi> Nor let the ſence of your own unworthineſs deter you from par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of ſo great a Treaſure, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remember that our Saviour hath promiſed, <hi>not to break the bruiſed Reed, nor to quench the ſmoaking flax: That he will receive him that is weak in the Faith:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 14.1.</note> And pray with Chriſts Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:63173:85"/>
                  <hi>Lord increaſe my Faith:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 17.5.</note> And with the Father of the Lunatick,
<note place="margin">Mar. 9.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, help thou my unbelief:</hi> And then with a full Truſt and Reliance on God, ſay with the Apoſtle;
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.12.</note> 
                  <hi>I know whom I have believed, and I am perſwaded that he is able to keep that, which I have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto him, against that day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> When the Devil hath tryed all other Temptations in vain, he may perhaps raiſe doubts in your mind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the truth of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and ſo by ruining the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, endeavour to overthrow the whole Superſtructure of your Faith. Which if Satan doth, do not enter into a diſpute with him, but conſider well the weakneſs of Humane underſtanding, and its igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance even in natural things: And on the other hand, the infinite Wiſdom and Power of God, far exceeding our Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, and his Eternal Truth, which cannot deceive nor be deceived: Call to mind the Sacred Myſteries of our Religion, which were revealed unto us by the Prophets and Apoſtles, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Miracles, more eſpecially in the life of our Bleſſed Saviour, all which receive with a firm Faith without any doubtfulneſs; and pray unto God, that
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:63173:85"/>he would pleaſe to Aid and Aſſiſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities of your Faith, and aſſure you by the inward Teſtimony of his Holy Spirit, that the Sacred Scriptures are Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely inſpired by his word, which, with the Sacraments, are a means of beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and confirming this belief in you.</p>
               <p>After the ſick Perſon is thus Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unto God, and by a firm truſt in the Mercies of God, and the Merits of Chriſt hath arm'd his mind againſt ſin, the Devil, and other Temptations; it will be fitting farther to ſtrengthen himſelf againſt ſome others, which often hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to dying Perſons: Which will be beſt done, if inſtead of thinking any more on Death it ſelf, he rather transfers his thoughts, and fixes them on the moſt Happy State of the Heavenly life, to which he is haſtning:
<note place="margin">Apoc. 14.13.</note> For <hi>Bleſſed are the Dead which die in the Lord; they reſt from their Labours, and their Works follow them:</hi> For although Death be the Wages of Sin, yet by the Death of Chriſt it is changed into a happy paſſage to a true life; by which being ſet looſe from the Priſon of this World, from the Bondage of Trouble, and from the Chains of ſin, we come unto Chriſt: By the Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Corporeal Tabernacle, we
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:63173:86"/>are Tranſlated from our Earthly Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, to dwell for ever with the Lord: By Death we leave this valley of Tears, this Dungeon of Miſery, and mount up to the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> where there is no crying, nor pain, nor Death, but perpetual Pleaſures, and rejoycing for evermore: Hence the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle truly calls Death, the <hi>gain</hi> of the godly; for is it not great gain to leave evil things, and to poſſeſs an infinite good?</p>
               <p>The ſick Perſon may perhaps be ſad and melancholly, when he thinks that he muſt now endure a great deal of pain, and when he is dead, muſt be left by all his Friends, and Travel alone into an unknown Region; but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him againſt this, let him conſider, that he enjoys the preſence of God, and the Divine aſſiſtance, according to Gods promiſe, that the Bleſſed Angels will wait on him, to Conduct his Soul to the Pallace of the Great King; for <hi>they are all Miniſtring Spirits,
<note place="margin">Heb. 1. ult.</note> ſent forth to Miniſter unto thoſe who ſhall be Heirs of Salvation.</hi> That as no Body is born into the World by chance, ſo doth no body die by chance neither, but that Diſeaſes and Death happen to us by
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:63173:86"/>Gods appointment: And let him Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on ſuch Texts of Scripture as theſe. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord;
<note place="margin">Iſa. 43.1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> when thou paſſest through the Waters, I will be with thee, and through the Rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee: When thou walkest through the fire, thou ſhall not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee. Call upon me in the day of Trouble,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 50.15.</note> I will deliver thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me. Though I walk through the Valley of the ſhaddow of Death I will fear no Evil,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 23.4.</note> for thou art with me.
<note place="margin">Pſ. 43. ult.</note> Why art thou caſt down O my Soul, and why art thou diſquieted within me? Hope in God, for I ſhall yet praiſe him, who is the health of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and my God.
<note place="margin">Pſ. 73.25.</note> Whom have I in Heaven but thee? And there is none up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth that I deſire beſides thee.
<note place="margin">verſ. 26.</note> My Fleſh and my Heart faileth, but God is the strength of my Heart, and my portion for ever.
<note place="margin">verſ. 28.</note> It is good for me to draw near to God: I have put my Truſt in the Lord God.
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.29. verſ. 30. verſ. 31. Joh. 8.51.</note> One Sparrow ſhall not fall to the ground without your Father, and the very hairs of your Head, are all numbred. Fear ye not therefore. Verily, verily, I ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, if a Man keep my ſaying, he ſhall never ſee Death:</hi> That is, not only he ſhall not ſee Eternal Death, but alſo
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:63173:87"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:63173:87"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:63173:88"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:63173:88"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:63173:89"/>ſhall not feel the bitterneſs of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Death.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.31: 2 Chr. 20.21.</note> 
                  <hi>If God be for us, who can be against us. O our God, we know not what to do, but our Eyes are upon thee.
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.9.</note> The Lord knoweth how to deliver the Godly out of Temptations. Shall we receive good at the hand of God,
<note place="margin">Job 2.10.1.21. Job 13.15. Job 19.25.</note> and ſhall we not receive evil? Bleſſed be the Name of the Lord. Though he ſlay me, yet will I truſt in him: I know that my Redeemer liveth, and though after my skin worms deſtroy this Body, yet in my fleſh ſhall I ſee God.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.13.</note> God is faithful, who will not ſuffer you to be Tempted above that ye are able, but will with the Temptation alſo make away to eſcape that ye may be able to bear it:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe you ſhould feel ſome of the cruel pangs of Death, yet conſider that they befal you by the Will of God, to whom the very Hairs of our Head are known, and without whoſe Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, nothing in the World happens. That they are Tokens of Gods Favour, rather than his Anger;
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.6.</note> 
                  <hi>for whom the Lord loveth, he chaſteneth.</hi> However theſe pains are very ſhort and Momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, and by them we have admiſſion into Eternal life: Our Nativity is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with Sorrow and Crying: But
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:63173:89"/>the ſharper theſe pangs are, the ſooner they will be over, and then ſucceeds everlaſting Joy and Gladneſs:
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> 
                  <hi>For I reckon that the ſufferings of this preſent time, are not worthy to be compared with the glory which ſhall be revealed in us.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.16.</note> For which cauſe we faint not, but though our outward Man periſh,
<note place="margin">verſ. 17.</note> yet the inward Man is renewed day by day. For our light af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, which is but for a Moment, encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth for us a far more exceeding and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal weight of glory. If we die with him, we ſhall alſo live with him.
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.11.</note> We muſt through much Tribulation, enter into the Kingdom of God; and the God of all grace,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.10.</note> who hath called us unto his Eternal glory by Chriſt Jeſus, after that ye have ſuffered a while, will Eſtabliſh, Strengthen and Settle you.</hi> Chronical Diſeaſes may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps be troubleſome and painful for ſome time; yet all, even the longeſt are but a moment in reſpect of Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: <hi>Therefore wait on the Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 27.14.</note> be of good courage, and he ſhall ſtrengthen thine Heart, wait, I ſay, on the Lord:</hi> For though he ſhould ſeem <hi>to hide his face from thee for a Moment,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 54.8.</note> yet with everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindneſs, will he have Mercy on thee. His anger may endure for a Moment,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 30.5.</note> but in his favour is life, weeping may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:63173:90"/>for a Night, but joy cometh in the Morning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any ſhould be concern'd, leaſt in the agony of Death, their Ears ſhould be deaf, and their Senſes fail them, and ſo ſhould be deſtitute of neceſſary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations; let them remember, that <hi>the Spirit it ſelf will bear witneſs with our Spirits,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.26.</note> that we are the Children of God: Likewiſe the Spirit alſo helpeth our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, for we know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought, but the Spirit it ſelf ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth interceſſion for us, with groanings which cannot be uttered.</hi> He is the true and only <hi>Comforter;</hi> who when our Eyes are darkned, inlightens our Heart, when our Ears are ſhut, will ſpeak Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation to our Souls. Let them alſo attentively meditate on what our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaid a little before his Paſſion, <hi>Now is the Prince of this World judged;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 16.11.</note> that is, he who brought Death into the World is overcome by my Death, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and is deprived of all power of hurting:
<note place="margin">Joh. 10.27, 28.</note> As alſo: <hi>My ſheep hear my voice, and I know them, and they follow me: And I give unto them Eternal life, and they ſhall never periſh:</hi> And therefore he may ſay with <hi>David;
<note place="margin">Pſ. 27.1.3.</note> the Lord is my light, and my Salvation, whom ſhall I fear?
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:63173:90"/>The Lord is the strength of my life, of whom ſhall I be afraid? Though an Host ſhould encamp againſt me, my Heart ſhall not fear. Yea,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 23.4.</note> though I walk through the Valley of the ſhaddow of Death, I will fear no Evil; for thou art with me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is often a great trouble to Men when they are dying, to think that they muſt leave their Wife and Children, their Brethren and Siſters, their Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Friends: But whereas this care proceeds either firſt from that natural Sympathy which we bear to thoſe we love; or elſe from a fear, that our Wife and Children ſhould ſuffer damage for want of our Advice and Aſſiſtance: It is therefore fit in the firſt place to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, what hath been before ſpoken of,
<note place="margin">Chap. 14.</note> that we are to love God above all things, and not to ſet our Affections up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Creature more than God: Of this our Saviour Admoniſhes us.
<note place="margin">Luke 14.26.</note> 
                  <hi>If any Man come to me, and hate not his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Mother, and Wife, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and Brethren, and Siſters, yea, and his own life alſo, he cannot be my Diſciple.</hi> Neither are we quite ſeparated from our Friends by Death, but we ſhall be again united to them in the other life, and not to them only, but we ſhall alſo enter
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:63173:91"/>into the Society of Angels and Bleſſed Spirits. In the ſecond place it ought to be conſidered,
<note place="margin">Pſa. 68.5.</note> that <hi>a Father of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs, and a judge of the Widow, is God in his Holy Habitation.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every one ought to commend their Relations to his Care and Protection. God, who is your God, will be alſo the God of your Poſterity. Hear what the Royal Prophet ſaith:
<note place="margin">Pſ. 37.25.</note> 
                  <hi>I have been young, and now am old, yet have I not ſeen the Righteous forſaken, nor his Seed begging bread.
<note place="margin">Pſ. 112.2.</note> The generation of the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right ſhall be Bleſſed.
<note place="margin">Pſ. 10.18.</note> Thou wilt judge the Fatherleſs and the Oppreſſed.
<note place="margin">Pſ. 146.9.</note> The Lord preſerveth the Strangers, he relieveth the Fatherleſs and Widow.</hi> To this purpoſe ſpeaketh <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 10.17, 18.</note> ſaying, <hi>the Lord your God, is a God of Gods, and Lord of Lords, a great God and mighty. He doth execute the Judgment of the Fatherleſs and Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and loveth the Stranger, in giving him Food and Rayment.</hi> And by the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah.
<note place="margin">Jer. 49.11.</note> Thus ſaith the Lord, leave thy Fatherleſs Children: I will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them alive, and let thy Widows trust in me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to what concerns the Body, the ſick perſon ought to take what care he can of his life, ſo long as it laſts: For
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:63173:91"/>to live or die, is not in our own power; as ſaith St. <hi>Paul,
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.7, 8.</note> None of us liveth to himſelf, and no Man dieth to himſelf; for whether we live, we live unto the Lord, and whether we die, we die unto the Lord, whether we live therefore or die we are the Lords.</hi> So that our life is diligently to be regarded, until he that gave it, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it of us again; and the great Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the World call us hence: And therefore thoſe Helps and Proviſions which God hath allowed by Phyſick and Phyſitians for the preſervation of Health, are not to be deſpiſed. Though in the mean time, the ſick Man ought not to flatter himſelf with certain hopes of recovering his health, nor ſhould his Friends put the thoughts of Death out of his mind, and confidently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe him longer life; for a Man thus perſwaded that his life is not in danger, will eaſily be drawn off, from fitting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for an happy Death; and if after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it ſhould happen that an unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Death ſhould ſeize on him, and notwithſtanding his vain hopes, and the aſſurances of his Friends, he ſees that he muſt die, he would hereby impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently bear the Hand of God upon him, and might run the hazard of his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:63173:92"/>Welfare: It is therefore very requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite for him wholly to commit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Divine Will and Diſpoſal, and often revolve in his mind the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited paſſage of St. <hi>Paul,
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.8.</note> Whether we live, or whether we die, we are the Lords:</hi> And if his ſickneſs be any thing dubious, he ought rather to be ſolicitous how he may die, than how he may recover his health, ſaying with the Apoſtle: <hi>This one thing I do forgetting thoſe things which are behind,
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.13.</note> and reaching forth unto thoſe things which are before,
<note place="margin">verſe 14.</note> I preſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the mark for the prize of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We come now to that other Duty which is incumbent on the dying Man; and this reſpects his Neighbour, which is twofold; the firſt is, that he recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciles himſelf to all, and from his Heart forgives all Injuries and Offences what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; that he deſires forgiveneſs from all whom he hath offended; and that he doth not ſo much conſider how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriouſly he hath been uſed by this or that Perſon, as how many and grievous things there are, which he hath need to beg Pardon at Gods hands for.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is, that they who are Magiſtrates and Governours over others,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:63173:92"/>do ſo diſpoſe their Affairs, that the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Offices which God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them, be fully diſcharged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they die, and that they take care as much as in them lies, that the peace of the Church be ſecur'd; and that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Juſtice be preſerv'd ſound and entire, after the Example of <hi>Moſes, Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua, David,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>He who is the Maſter of a Family, ought to ſettle every thing under his Care, and think that what <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Hezechiah,</hi> is ſaid alſo to him;
<note place="margin">Iſa. 38.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Set thine Houſe in Order, for thou ſhalt die, and not live.</hi> And therefore let him endeavour what he can, to agree things that are to be agreed, and to ſet in order ſuch things as are conſus'd. But if it ſhould happen that any one ſhould be ſo invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in a multiplicity of intricate Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, that he cannot apply his mind to them, and take care of his Soul too; it will be much better to diſpatch his Worldly Buſineſs quickly, or rather to caſt off all care for his Earthly concerns, and wholly give up himſelf to provide for the Eternal good of his Soul: Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the advice of our Saviour, <hi>Seek ye first the Kingdom of God,
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.33. Mat. 8.23.</note> and his Righteouſneſs:</hi> And. <hi>Follow me, and let
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:63173:93"/>the Dead, bury their Dead.</hi> There will be enough left to order and compoſe the things of this World; but no Man can repair the loſs of Eternal Salvation, which depends upon a Reconciliation with God: But if Worldly Buſineſs may be done without any hurt to the Soul; in the firſt place, let him diſpoſe of his goods, and if it be needful, make his Will, which ought to be plain and intelligible, comformable to the Law of Nature, to the Word of God, and to the Laws of the Country wherein he lives, that ſo there may be no occaſion given to his Heirs and Executors, to have any Litigious Diſputes and Law-Suits after his Death; and this he ought to do, whilſt his Mind, and Tongue, and Hand, can perform their Functions, and not to defer it till he is not able to make his mind known clearly and diſtinctly, either by word or writing: And indeed they do moſt conveniently, and to the purpoſe, who make their Wills whilſt they are in perfect health; on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary they very ill conſult their own Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, who put off the making of their Wills, till ſome dangerous ſickneſs aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults them, and then perhaps they are ſuddenly taken out of the World, or the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:63173:93"/>Diſeaſe cauſes a Frenzie, and ſo their minds become utterly indiſpos'd for the ſettling of their Worldly concerns.</p>
               <p>If the ſick Perſon remembers that he hath taken any thing away from any Man wrongfully, let him reſtore it again to the right owner, or if he be Dead, and that cannot well be done, let him appoint it to be given to pious uſes, to the poor of the Church or State: For as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Si res aliena, propter quam peccatum eſt, cum reddi poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, non reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, non agitur poenit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ntia ſed fingitur.</hi> Epiſt. 54. ad Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>don.</note> 
                  <hi>A Man is an Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, and not a true Penitent, if he doth not reſtore goods wrongfully taken, when it is in his power to do it.</hi> And let thoſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo who abound in Riches honeſtly got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, take care, that ſome portion of them be given to good and pious uſes, and that amongſt the reſt of their Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacies, ſomething be left and aſſigned to Chriſt. Moreover the ſick Perſon ought to look after ſuch things as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Souls of thoſe under his care, and to commend unto all his Family, that Religion which is contained in the Word of God, and diligently to exhort them to a Holy life, to the love and ſervice of God: Although as it hath been ſaid, ſuch things were better to be ordered, and provided for, when we are well and in good Health; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:63173:94"/>Death takes away many on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and ſome Diſeaſes are of ſuch a Nature, that they preſently deprive a Man of the power of thinking on, and ordering ſuch things; ſo that it will be moſt ſafe and prudent for the ſick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to put off all thoughts of Earthly things, and not to diſtract himſelf with any cares, but to fix his mind wholly upon God, and on his happy paſſage out of this life.</p>
               <p>And now when the ſick Man finds his end approaching, that the time of his departure is at hand, and that he is now to ſtruggle with the pangs of Death, laying aſide all Worldly cares, let him intirely ſubmit himſelf to Gods Will, and in no wiſe withſtand it; and ſay, Father, thy Will be done, whether it be by Life or by Death: And then let him endeavour that he may die in the Faith of Chriſt, and reſt in the Lord; that is, let him give himſelf up wholly to the grace and mercy of God, in the Merits of Chriſt, and to the Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Holy Spirit: For ſince in that laſt hour, this World and all things in it, Friends and Relations, Riches and Pleaſures, and whatever elſe is taking and delightful, muſt be quite abandon'd,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:63173:94"/>it is very fitting that his mind ſhould bid farewel to all things here below, and by Faith lift up it ſelf to God alone: And the Man being thus plac'd as it were out of himſelf, he ought with the moſt earneſt Affections, and with the moſt Ardent Prayers, and Fervent Sighs to fly unto the Mercy and Goodneſs of God, and ſay with <hi>David,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 73.26.</note> My Fleſh and my Heart faileth, but God is the ſtrength of my Heart, and my Portion for ever. In thee O Lord do I put my trust,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 31.1.</note> let me never be put to Confuſion, deliver me in thy Righteouſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then at laſt when he is juſt going out of the World, let him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his Soul unto God, as unto a faithful Creatour, and moſt Merciful Saviour, and ſay with Chriſt. <hi>Father,
<note place="margin">Luk. 23.46.</note> into thy Hands I commend my Spirit:</hi> And with St.
<note place="margin">Act. 7.59.</note> 
                  <hi>Stephen Lord Jeſus receive my Spirit:</hi> If any of the foregoing Temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tations ſhould be ſuggeſted by Satan to the ſick Perſon, when he lies under the agonies of Death, let him not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himſelf to give an anſwer, but commit himſelf wholly to Chriſt, and depend only upon him, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere to the laſt in pious Prayers and Ejaculations: As alſo thoſe that are
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:63173:95"/>preſent with him ought to do, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when they find his ſenſes begin to fail him: For the <hi>Prayers of the Righteous avail much,</hi> and our Lord hath promiſed, that <hi>where two or three are gathered together in his Name, there will he be in the midſt of them,</hi> and that <hi>whatſoever we ask of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his Name, he will give it us:</hi> Now where-ever Chriſts gracious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is, the Devil of neceſſity muſt flee before him: Neither can the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil tempt any Man beyond what God permits him: And therefore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one ought not to be admitted to the ſick Perſon when he is at the point of Death, but only ſuch who are Religious, who by Devout Prayers can commend the departing Soul to God, but ſuch are not to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to come to him, who may in the leaſt excite in him an hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any Man, or a love towards any Worldly thing: Or if they are permitted to come to him, care muſt be taken that they behave themſelves ſo, as not to raiſe in his mind any evil affection, which he had before laid aſide and forſaken. For a Soul that would depart happily out of this
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:63173:95"/>life ought to be inflam'd with the love of God alone, and not to be mov'd either by the love or hatred of any Creature whatever.</p>
               <p>And more eſpecially let care be taken, that the Dying Man may be viſited and aſſiſted by ſome Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Gods Word, of good Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Judgment, that he may know how to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon to the wearied Soul, that he may ſo govern and temper his Diſcourſe, as neither to deceive the departing Soul by too much condeſcention and flattery, nor to drive him to deſpair by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable ſharpneſs and ſeverity, but may be able to inſtruct and fortifie him againſt all the Temptations of Satan, with Divine Counſels and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:63173:96"/>
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O Lord God and my moſt merciful Father, who haſt now ſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me the meſſenger of death, and haſt chastiſed me with ſickneſs; I confeſs my ſelf to be a grievous ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and that I have oftentimes of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended thee, even from my very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy; and therefore I acknowledge that this puniſhment is juſtly inflicted on me, and that I deſire death it ſelf; but I beſeech thee of thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercies, blot out all my tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions. O Lord rebuke me not in thine anger, neither chaſten me in thy hot diſpleaſure: If I conſider what I have done, what I ſuffer is not ſo much: what I have committed is grievous; what I ſuffer is but light; righteous art thou, O Lord, and upright are thy judgments: O Lord,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:63173:96"/>deal not with me after my ſins, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reward me after mine iniquities, but according to the multitude of thy mercies think thou vpon me, O Lord, for thy goodneſs: Thou, God art my ſtrength and the horn of my Salvation: thou makeſt ſore, and bindeſt up, thou woundeſt and thy hand make whole, thou killeſt and makeſt alive, thou bringeſt down to the Grave, and bringeſt up: if therefore thou plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt to permit my Soul to remain any longer in this Earthly Tabernacle for thy Glory and Service, O Lord, help thy afflicted Servant, and give me patience: But if thou ſeeſt it fit to take away my Life thy Will be done, and let thy Servant depart in peace: Protect me againſt all the temptations and aſſaults of Satan with the Shield of thy mercy: Grant that my faith may not fail me, nor my hope be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, nor the weakneſs of my Nature be caſt down by the terrours of Death:
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:63173:97"/>but after my Eyes are dim my Tongue faulters, and my ſenſes have loſt their power and faculties, grant that my Mind and Soul may be continually fix'd on thee, and by the Aſſiſtance of thy Holy Spirit may be firmly united to thee, and with my laſt breath I may commend my Soul into thy hands, O Lord, who liveſt and reigneſt for ever and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section_of_prayer">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bleſſed Lord, foraſmuch as I muſt bid farewel to this World I commend unto Thee all mine. Thou who relieveſt the Fatherleſs and the Widow, be their Father and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector; It is not for me to intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with what is thy prerogative; but give me Grace to uſe all Diligence to make my own calling and election ſure before I go hence and be no more ſeen: All my other care I caſt upon Thee:
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:63173:97"/>Be thou pleas'd to provide for all mine: Bleſs them O Lord, and repleniſh their hearts with a godly fear and love of thy holy Name: Give them health of body, ſoundneſs of mind, and all good things which thou ſeeſt fit for them: Keep from them all ſuch things as may alienate their minds from Thee, or any ways hinder them from the profeſſion of a true faith, or the practice of a Holy Life.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section_of_prayer">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O Eternal Lord, I now ſee all things in the World leave me; but do not thou forſake me, O my God. In thee is my truſt, leave not my Soul deſtitute, I flee unto thee for ſuccour; Make haſt to help me, O Lord, my Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; O my God be not far from me, in this my laſt hour: I confeſs indeed I am not worthy to be called thy Son, or even the meaneſt of thy Servants;
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:63173:98"/>but I caſt my ſelf at thy feet, and fall down before thy Throne of Grace; O deal with me according the multitude of thy mercies, and enter not into judgment with thy Servant: I do not hide my tranſgreſſions from thee, but hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly confeſs them before thy Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty: but according to thy mercy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thou me, for thy goodneſs ſake, O Lord, look upon my affliction and pain, and forgive all my ſins, for the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and Death of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: Caſt me not away from thy thy preſence ſince thou haſt redeemed me with the blood of thy Son: O keep my Soul and deliver me, let me not be aſhamed for I put my truſt in thee. O dear Jeſu, thou art my Redeemer, and my Saviour; thou haſt overcome the World, Sin, and Hell it ſelf, that they can do me no harm: Lord, I come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, do not reject me; O do not leave me in this my hour of Death: Into thy hands I commend my Spirit: Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:63173:98"/>receive my Spirit.</hi> Amen. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  <q>O Man remember Death and Eternity; and whilſt you live here, conſider where, after Death you are to live for ever and ever.</q>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:63173:99"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and are to be Sold by <hi>Sam. Keble,</hi> at the <hi>Great Turks-head,</hi> in <hi>Fleet ſtreet.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>MONASTICON ANGLICANUM:</hi> Or, the Hiſtory of the Ancient Abbies, and other Monaſteries, Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, Cathedral, and Collegiate Churches in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales;</hi> with divers <hi>French, Iriſh,</hi> and <hi>Scotch</hi> Monaſteries formerly relating to <hi>England.</hi> Collected and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in <hi>Latin,</hi> by Sir <hi>William Dugdale,</hi> Knt. late Gartor King of Arms, in Three Volums, and now epitomiz'd in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Page by Page, price 10 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hiſtorical Parts of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament</hi> in Verſe, with One Hundred and Twenty Cuts, being the beſt uſe of Poetry and Sculpture, 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price. 2 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>EPICTETI Enchiridion:</hi> Or, the moſt Excellent Morals of <hi>Epictetus.</hi> Made <hi>Engliſh</hi> in a Poetical Paraphraſe. By <hi>Ellis Walker,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>A Collection of Private Forms of Prayers for Morning, Noon, and Night, and other ſpecial Occaſions by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Weeks Preparation</hi> to the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Degrees of Marriage, that which is ordered to be had in all Churches.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:63173:99"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
